<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the Jesuites life and doctrine by M.G.</title>
            <author>M. G. (Martin Grene), 1616-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41988</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1825</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12657</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13133527</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13133527</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41988)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 419:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the Jesuites life and doctrine by M.G.</title>
                  <author>M. G. (Martin Grene), 1616-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 149, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Martin Grene. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from BM.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Pages 5, 67, and 70 are tightly bound with loss of print in filmed copy. Beginning-page 15 and pages 60-75 photographed from Dr. Williams' Library copy and inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>AN ACCOUNT Of the JESUITES LIFE AND DOCTRINE.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>M. G.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year. 1661.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="modern_bookplate">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>bookplate</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:2"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
                  <p>THough the Progreſs of affairs in our late revolutions might have made every one plainly perceive whence the diſtempers of our times proceeded; yet many will needs conceive, or pretend they conceive, that the Papiſts were occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all our diſorders, and the Jeſuits the <hi>Boutefeu's</hi> in the ruine of both King and Country, What miſery the miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the Bible hath brought upon our Nation by a ſwarme of Sects, that Libels lay to Catholicks, the only Religion that conſtantly, none excepted, followed the Royall party? Priests and Jeſuits are ſaid to be the cauſe of all thoſe miſchiefs, of which the whole World know's, Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were the true Source: their restleſs Spirits never being content till having
<pb facs="tcp:97877:3"/>pryed on both Crown and Mitre, at length they worried one another. Yet 'tis the ſtile of our times to lay all to the Papiſts, and no Man concludes with applauſe, but he that Perorat's againſt the Jeſuits. Pamphlets are the Vulgar Oracles, and Libels the guide of thoſe that pretended to believe nothing but Bible. It is a ſtrange thing to ſee what Character is commonly given the Jeſuits. Every Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, ſay our Pamphlets and Pulpits too, hath a Pope in his belly, a <hi>Macchiavel</hi> in his head, <hi>Mercuries</hi> wings on his feet, and the Myſterious feather of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian's</hi> cocks tail in his hand. The Pope in his belly makes him ſtill big with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, still giving birth to ſome new miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief. <hi>Macchiavel</hi> in his head Orders all ſo dexterouſly as to make him out reach all the World. <hi>Mercurie's</hi> wings on his feet carry him from place to place, from Country to Country, and make him eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in a trice. The Cocks feather in his hand, opens all cloſets and Cofers, and Secrets, and diſcovers to the Jeſuit,
<pb facs="tcp:97877:3"/>the Want and Wealth of every one, that he may know where to place his labours with thrift. And if you ask, why the Jeſuits are never diſcovered in theſe pranks, the Libels tell you it is becauſe the Jeſuits have <hi>Proteus's</hi> bodies, and transforme themſelves into all ſhapes; Now a Cobler, now a Preacher, now a Tinker, now a Courtier, now a Peaſan, now a States-man, and what not? And this still with <hi>Gyges's</hi> ring on their finger, that they may never be ſeen but when they liſt. By this means it comes to paſs, that the Jeſuits can ſeldom or never be charged in particular with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſdemeanour; yet it is certain, <hi>credite poſteri;</hi> that they are the only contrivers of all the miſchiefs in the World. If the Covenant be in vogue none but Jeſuits, and Jeſuited Papiſts, reſist it. If the ſame covenant be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to deſerved flames, 'twas the Jeſuits made it, no body elſe could have dreamt of ſo much malice. If the King be cryed down in Pulpits and Tubs,
<pb facs="tcp:97877:4"/>for leavying an unnatural war againſt his dutifull Subjects, (as our late Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of glorious memory was) 'twas the Papists did all, and the Jeſuits were the Incendiaries. If three Kingdomes groan under the Tyranny of <hi>Cromwel,</hi> there were <hi>500</hi> Jeſuits in his Army. What more? Every crime is theirs. The Jeſuits are to our Fabulous heads, what the Evil-<hi>Genius's</hi> or Peſtiferous Gods were to old time,, when fictions made Deities. They are Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Epiſcopal Proteſtants, and Levellers, and Quakers, and what you will, provided it be (for that time) a name of diſgrace. They have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown learning, deſtroyed Philoſophy, poyſoned States, corrupted manners, betrayed Kingdoms, ſubverted the Church, coufounded the Goſpel, and as with the dregs of <hi>Pandora's</hi> box pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out more miſchief on the World then all the Devils in Hell could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have wiſhed. Thus ſay the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels:
<pb facs="tcp:97877:4"/>and why may not Libellers take the Liberty to ſpeak as largely in Proſe, as Poets do in verſe, ſpecially when they are backed from the Pulpits, and warmed with the zeal of the good old cauſe.</p>
                  <p>But fair and ſoftly: Is any thing of all this true? 'tis printed. Where? there be a thouſand books in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard that affirm all this, and more then this. And is that enough? How many books where there ſold in that place, and all <hi>England</hi> over, in which his late Sacred Majesty was made the cauſe of all our misfortunes? How many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Biſhops? How many against his Royal Majesty that now reigneth? Nay who is there of any merit in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> living or dead in our memory, whom Libels do not ſeek to defame? If it were enough to be accuſed, no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy would be innocent: 'tis a trade now a dayes to write ſlanders for a lively-hood, Many crimes are laid to the Jeſuits, but the Jeſuits deny them all. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb facs="tcp:97877:5"/>will judge right muſt hear both ſides, and then give his verdict. Till this be done an argument of the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its innocency is, that they challenge their Adverſaries to appear, and ſpeak to the particulars, and profer, that they will be content to be caſt if they be proved no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. On the contrary an argument of errour in thoſe that inveigh againſt the Jeſuits is, that they make it their first care to diſguiſe themſelves, they ſpeak behind the curtain, and rove in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall propoſitions, crying out against all without being able to inſtance in any.</p>
                  <p>I do not hope to ſtop the Torrent of Slandering tongues: the floud of a foul mouth is too impetuous to be ever dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med up in this World; yet I hope that I ſhall be able to vindicate the Society ſo far, as that, though fools still babble, yet wiſe men ſhall ſee they have no reaſon; and though malitious men still envy, yet all charitable Chriſtians ſhall plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive that the fault lyes on their ſide that reprehend Vertue and carp at
<pb facs="tcp:97877:5"/>learning, and impugne that, which they do not, or will not underſtand.</p>
                  <p>The means which I intend to take for to do this, is nothing elſe then to give a plain and true account of the Jeſuits Life and Doctrine, and to ſet down clearly what is objected against the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, and what they anſwer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>This I hope will ſatisfie: for I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it very true which <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. King of <hi>France</hi> uſually ſaid; That to know the Jeſuits, is enough for to make any body love them. I hope it may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to thoſe proteſtants that read this ſhort treatiſe, as <hi>Adam Conizen</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates that it happened to divers Miniſters in <hi>Germany;</hi> who when they had bought the Conſtitutions and Rules of the Society at <hi>Franckfurt</hi> fair, (which had been taken in ſome Colledge) they read them over with a great deal of eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and after all pronounced this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of them; That there was nothing there that could be reprehended, ſave
<pb facs="tcp:97877:6"/>only the Roman Religion. And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome will joyn with that great wit Sr. <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> once Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> who in his <hi>Advancement of Learning</hi> ſpeaketh thus of the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its. When I conſider their pains and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, as well in the culture of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as information of manners, the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> touuhing <hi>Pharnaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> comes into my mind. <hi>Talis cum ſis utinam noſter eſſes.</hi> But for the judgment I leave it to the Reader, my part ſhall only be to give a candide nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And beſides the love to truth which I have, I reflect that all thoſe who during their long exile abroad with his Majesty, had acquaintance with the Jeſuits, would diſprove me if I ſhould ſay any thing contrary to what they know and have ſeen of the Society. I ſhall therefore ſay nothing of them, but what I know to be true, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal nothing that I think may ſeem to give a full knowledge of the Jeſuits, as far as can be compriſed in a ſhort treatiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:97877:6"/>I have not meddled with the Engliſh Jeſuits, and ſcarce named them. The reaſon is, becauſe I do not ſee anything of moment objected to them particularly. They have been alwayes faithfull at home, and dutifull abroad, as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath been often graciouſly pleaſed to expreſs. Though many have cryed them down as the publick Incendiaries, yet it is moſt manifeſt that never any one of them ſided with the Kings Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but as far as they could by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their friends they abbetted the Royal party. They were in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Camp, where ſome of them lost their lives, others being taken, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red impriſonment, and other hardſhip. There is ſcarce one Jeſuit in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> who cannot reckon ſome of his neereſt Relations that dyed for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, and none whoſe kindred and Friends were not ruined in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes for the ſame quarrel. And all that depended on the Jeſuits ſided with his Majeſty. Among theſe were ſome
<pb facs="tcp:97877:7"/>ſignal perſons, as Sr. <hi>Henry Gage,</hi> Sr. <hi>John Smith,</hi> Sr. <hi>John Digby,</hi> who having been formerly Scholars of the Society, were actually when they dyed Penitents of the Jeſuits. And Mr. <hi>Peter Wright,</hi> who was executed at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> was particularly maligned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was Sir <hi>Henry Gage's</hi> Prieſt. As for Perſons of prime Nobility, who loſt great Estates, and endured much hardſhip for his Majeſty, The late Dutcheſſe of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the late Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> the late Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> were Penitents of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, to ſay nothing of others. On the contrary the Rebels preached every where against the Jeſuits, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they took any of them, they impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and executed them; ſo that I do not ſee any need to prove their Loyalty. Certainly if they had had any principles of Rebellion in their heart, they would in theſe publick revolutions have ſhewed them at one time or other. Yet though for loyalty I conceive them blameleſs, I will
<pb facs="tcp:97877:7"/>not ſay, but that happily the indiſcretion of ſome may have deſerved a cenſure: but I hope that the errours of a few, will not riſe in judgment, and countervail the merits of a long tried fidelity in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. I confeſſe I have heard ſome mutter ſomething of the errours of ſome En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Jeſuits abroad, for which they feared all might ſmart. Yet where ſins of blackeſt malice have found indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, I hope indiſcretions will not be remembred. That Royal clemency that could indemnifie Rebels, and bury in oblivion, unparrelled injuries done to his Father and himſelf, by perfidious and Sacrilegious Subjects, will doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe be a Sanctuary to all that ask par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for thoſe errours which have been incurred without malice. This I ſay, on ſuppoſition that there may have been ſome errours which I know not of. We are all men, and as men we may err; we are alſo Christians, and as ſuch we ought to pardon. It is with this mind that I deſire the Reader to peruſe
<pb facs="tcp:97877:8"/>this little tract, conſulting ſtill with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and charity, both which ought to joyn in every Christian cenſure.</p>
                  <p>I have nothing more to add; but only that whereas my mind doth give me, that ſome (that malice the Jeſuits and would have them alone excluded from the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of free born Subjects, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the publick clemency) will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour an anſwer to what I have here ſaid; all that I deſire of them, is this, that they will be pleaſed to have a care to ſay nothing but what they can make good, as I do undertake for all that I have here writ. I do not flatter my weakneſs ſo, as to think I have ſaid well, yet my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence dictateth that I have ſaid true. And in that ſence I ſhall be willing to juſtifie every thing that I have here ſaid, and if perhaps (through humane frailty) I have erred in any thing, I ſhall humbly acknowledge it, and thank him that ſhall ſhew me my errour.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:8"/>
                  <head>An Account of the JESUITS <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CAP. I.</hi> Of the Author and end of the Society of Jeſus.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IGnatius</hi> of <hi>Loyola,</hi> Founder of the Society of Jeſus, born of a good Family in <hi>Biſcay,</hi> being a Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Year 1521. received a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Wound. Whilſt he was under the Surgeons hands in a long cure he chanced to read ſome good books: if notwithſtanding we may call that a chance, which was by a ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God ordained for his good, and the Salvation of many. For theſe Books inflamed his heart ſo with thoughts of Eternity, with the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Sin, with the example of Saints, with the love of God, that he was ſuddainly Metamorphoſed into
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97877:9"/>another Man, and reſolved on a new life. Being therefore at length reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, he ſet hand to work, and put in Execution what in his Infirmity he had projected. Inſtantly ſtripping him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all the goods that formerly he enjoyed or hoped in this World; and quitting houſe and Home, in a poor beggarly Weed, he went to <hi>Manreſa,</hi> where he was unknown to all the World. There in an Hoſpital, to which he had Voluntarily offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to tend the ſick, he lead a moſt ſtrict life, and made it his ſtudy to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due himſelf as much as poſſibly he could. He went bare foot, and bare head, pittifully clad, and lodged on the cold ground. He prayed ſeven hours a day on his knees, uſed frequent mortifications of hair-ſhirts, chains, and diſciplines. Except Sundayes, he faſted every day; though even on the Sundays too, his dyet was as bad as a faſt, for he never eat any thing but what he begged of Almes, and of that the beſt he gave to the poor, and himſelf lived on the refuſe which ſeemed not good enough to give to the beggars.</p>
                     <p>All this he did for to ſurmount him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97877:9"/>and learn perfectly that leſſon which Chriſt hath made the firſt for all thoſe that in his School will ſtudy perfection, <hi>Si quis vult venire Poſt me abneget ſemetipſum, &amp; tollat crucem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quotidie,</hi> Luc. 9.23. <hi>He that will follow me, let him renounce himſelf and take up his Croſs every day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whilſt he thus ſacrificed himſelf in the fire of divine love, God, who is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver behind hand with his ſervants, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed his ſoul with many ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gifts, and illuminated him with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of celeſtiall lights. As faſt as he went out of himſelf, ſo faſt he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the ſecret myſteries of God and Chriſt, in which as in a moſt perfect prototypon he ſaw the Idea of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety which he was afterwards to found. His firſt thought by which he ſteered all his actions, and which ſeemed as a beacon for all the courſe of his life, was a profound knowledg of his end. In that divine light which God ſtreamed upon him in his daily contemplations, he clearly ſaw how the infinite goodneſs of God according to his everlaſting Councels, in the beginning of time drew the whole world out of nothing,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97877:10"/>and created man for no other end then to love and ſerve his Lord and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in this life, and afterwards to enjoy him in perpetuall eternities. From this thought he drew a reſolution, to make this noble end of his the meaſure of all his actions, the firſt and laſt of all his thoughts, and the onely aim of all his deſires. To this his underſtanding, to this his memory, to this his will, to this his whole ſoul was ſo totally applied, that he was even abſorpt in this thought of ſeeking his laſt end, that is his God. And as the love of God, is of all things imaginable the moſt active and moſt noble; he could not endure to beſtow himſelf ſparingly on God. His deſign therefore was to do whatſoever he could imagine to be moſt advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to forward him towards his end, and moſt to the increaſe of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory of God. Hence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded that motto of his which was the firſt rule that he ever prefixed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Ad Majorem Dei Gloriam. To the greater Honour of God.</hi> By this motto or deviſe he intended two things. The firſt was that whenſoever any thing came into deliberation, he was to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97877:10"/>chooſe, not that which was moſt for his eaſe, or profit, or honour, but that which conſulting with reaſons of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, might appear moſt for the Honour and Glory of God. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing intended by him in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe was, that he was to make account that he was never to reſt in this World, never to think he had done enough, but ſtill to increaſe and go on, <hi>ad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem,</hi> to the greater and ſtill greater glory of God, by every good action enflaming his deſires to do yet better, and more for Gods honour. So was this firſt thought of his (the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his end) like the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> in the Heavens, the Superiour Orbe, which with his motion ſets all the inferiour Orbes a going; it was like the ſpring to the Watch of his Life, which being once well wound up, made all the Wheels of his ſeveral actions go well, and the <hi>Index</hi> of his good intention point right every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his life: it was like the Sun which gave Light, Vigour, and life, to all the Sphere of employments which he ever undertook.</p>
                     <p>After then that he was well fixed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97877:11"/>and radicated in this firſt thought, and had made ſuch reſolutions as did flow from it; his next ſolicitude was by what means he ſhould beſt compaſs this end in the perfecteſt manner that he could imagine, which might tend moſt to the glory of God. Here he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected, that certainly the beſt way to find God, was to follow Chriſt, and the nearer he came to Chriſt, the nearer he judged himſelf to be to the deſign he had laid of conſecrating all his life to Gods greater glory. This then was his ſecond thought, out of which he drew this reſolution, to take Chriſt for his pattern, and mould all his actions on the example which he ſhould ſee in Chriſt, whoſe Divinity and humanity were to be unto him the two Tables of the Law of the higheſt perfection. Meditating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore daily on the life of Chriſt, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured alwayes to copy out in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſomething of that which he ſaw in contemplation. The humility of Chriſt, the meekneſs, the modeſty, the temperance, the mercy, the obedience, the fortitude, were all as ſo many leſſons which he ſtudied to get by heart. And
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97877:11"/>in all he profited ſo well, that he left to poſterity admirable examples, ſo that he may juſtly ſay with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>imitatores mei eſtote ſicut ego Chriſti;</hi> Imitate you me as I have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itated Chriſt. But above all he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and admired the immenſe charity of Chriſt, that could make him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt himſelf of his own glory, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo a painfull life and death, for no other boon but the good of Souls. This he no ſooner obſerved but that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to joyn his labours with the labours of his Redeemer, and as far as humane frailty would give him leave to co-operate with Chriſt for the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Souls.</p>
                     <p>Here were then the two Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall thoughts, which were like the two poles on which all the life of this great Saint was turned. The firſt he drew from the conſideration of his Creation, the ſecond from looking on his Redemption: the firſt inflamed him with a zeal of Gods greater glory, the ſecond ſhewed him that this aim of Gods great glory muſt determine in the imitation of Chriſt, and co-opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with him for the good of ſouls.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97877:12"/>Having then reſolved on theſe two thoughts, and ſet them down as rules for his future life, there occurred to his mind two main difficulties. Firſt he obſerved how very unfit he was to think of ſetting on the converſion of ſouls. He had been trained up from his Infancy in the Court, and the Camp, two ſchools where the Goſpel is little thought on. Yet without a good underſtanding of the Goſpel to be got with long ſtudy, he ſaw he could neither have authority with others, nor ſecurity for himſelf. The myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of faith are obſcure and hard, and it were preſumption to adventure to explicate thoſe myſteries without having firſt learnt them well; And he had not yet read his Accidents. What ſhould he do? Being above thirty years old he begins the firſt rudiments with little children, and goeth on to the end of Divinity. Labour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy carried him through, that which no man would eaſily have ventured on, ſpecially in the circumſtances he was in. For having already made a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of voluntary poverty, he was forced to beg his bread from door to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97877:12"/>door, he continued ſtill his ſervent prayer, and faſt, and other mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and oftentimes interrupted his ſtudies with acts of Charity; yet at length with above ten years labour he ſurmounted the difficulty, and got to ſuch a pitch in learning as might give him both ſecurity in handling Divine myſteries and authority.</p>
                     <p>The other difficulty in the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe of the converſion of ſouls, was greater, and not to be overcome by one Man. His zeal compaſſed all the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, he deſired to co-operate with Chriſt for the Salvation of Souls in all the quarters of the World, and if poſſible in all ages to come; but being alone he could not do this, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to one place, and one life of a ſhort and uncertain durance. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he reſolved to communicate his deſires with ſuch as God ſhould inſpire to joyn with him, and to erect an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Religious men, which ſhould do that alwayes, and every where, which alone, he could do but in one place, and for the date of only one life. With this thought he looked about for ſuch as might be fit for his deſign, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97877:13"/>whilſt he was a Student at <hi>Paris</hi> he won to himſelf nine others, all men of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent vertue and learning, among them one was <hi>Francis Xaverius.</hi> With theſe he laid the foundation of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious order which he would have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Society of Jeſus. The reaſon of this name was not any thing elſe, then that all his order ſhould ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that as they were by the grace of Chriſt Jeſus called to this courſe of life, ſo they ought alwayes to look on Jeſus, and endeavour to conforme themſelves, as much as poſſibly might be, to the life of Jeſus: this imitation being that which St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed himſelf, as the beſt means to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to his ſinal end of Gods greater Glory.</p>
                     <p>After therefore that he and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions had given many ſingular proofs of their vertue, at length Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third, in the year 1540 erected the ſociety into a Relgious order, which he and his ſucceſſours the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Popes often confirmed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with many priviledges under the name of the ſociety of Jeſus. The end of this ſociety may ſufficiently appear
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97877:13"/>out of what I have ſaid, and it is ſe down by St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> in theſe words related <hi>in ſum. Conſtit. Finis hujus ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis est non ſolum ſaluti &amp; perfectioni propriarum animarum cum divina gratia vacare; ſed cum eadem impenſe in ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; perfectionem proximorum incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere. The end of this ſociety is not only to attend, with the divine grace, to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and perfection of our owne ſoules, but alſo with the ſame divine grace to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour earneſtly for the ſalvation and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of our neighbour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is the end of the ſociety, which I ſuppoſe no body can in reaſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt. For what more laudable then to endeavour Gods greater glory, and that in the Salvation of ſouls? It was this that God aimed at in the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of this all, this Chriſt looked at in the whole courſe of his life, and in his precious death; this is the end of the Goſpel, this mans ſole good, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this nothing is good, and in this is all good. Sin and Damnation are the worſt of evils which the Devil and thoſe that co-operate with him lead men unto; on the contrary vertue and Salvation are the greateſt Goods which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97877:14"/>Chriſt and thoſe that joyn their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours with his do lead unto: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, he that will complain of the Jeſuits for conſecrating their labours to the good and Salvation of their neighbours, muſt confeſs that he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not what the name of vertue means; he muſt allow that he is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of reaſon, and grant that he hath renounced his own nature, and under the ſhape of a Man is become a Wolf or Tygre, or even an incarnate Devil; there being none but the Devil that hareth the Salvation of mankind, and all thoſe that endeavour to co-operate with Chriſt to that end.</p>
                     <p>When I ſay, <hi>co-operate with Chriſt,</hi> no man muſt be ſcandalized as at an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent term. It is a word ordinarily uſed by thoſe who would expreſs the nature and dignity of an Apoſtolical Vocation. So <hi>Richardus a S. Victore</hi> ſaith, <hi>Neſcio an majus bonum poſſit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini a Deo conferri, quam ut per ejus obſequium alii conſequantur ſalutem, ſi ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Deo co-operentur ex charitate. I know not whether God beſtow any thing greater on man, than that others by his means obtain Salvation, if notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97877:14"/>he co-operate with God out of Charity.</hi> So alſo doth St. <hi>Dionyſe</hi> expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Caeleſt. Hierarchiae,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Omnium Dominus est Dei co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem fieri,</hi> it is the moſt divine work that man can do to co-operate with God; he ſpeaketh of labouring for the good of Souls, and cireth thoſe words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. <hi>Dei ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutores ſumus. We are the Co-adjutours of Almighty God.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> meant not that God needeth our help, but that he is pleaſed to uſe the help of men, and make one the inſtrument of the Salvation of others, which St. <hi>Dionyſe</hi> calleth the moſt divine work that man can do; and <hi>Hugo de S. Victore,</hi> the greateſt gift of God.</p>
                     <p>All this I conceive maketh it clear, that no man can with reaſon repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the aim and end of the Society. It remaineth therefore that we ſee whether the Society uſeth convenient means to attain this end; for if the end be good, and the means to attain that end be alſo good, it will follow that the whole inſtitute is good, and not only irreprehenſible, but alſo laudable.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97877:15"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CAP. II.</hi> By what means the Society endeavoureth to make their own fit Inſtruments for their end.</head>
                     <p>TWO things therefore are to be treated of, for to ſhew what means the Society uſeth for to compaſs her end. Firſt how the ſubjects of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety are trained up to be made fit In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for the Glory of God in the converſion of Souls. And ſecondly, when we have ſeen how they endeavor to perfect themſelves, we are farther to obſerve, what it is they do for the good of their neighbour. The firſt of theſe two things we will do in this chapter, the ſecond in the enſuing chapter.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> then obſerved that all the miſeries in which the Souls of men are involved ſpring chiefly from two fountains, ignorance, and vice. Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance like Ice freezeth up the Soul, and benummeth it into a dull ſtupidity. And as Ice doth eaſily thaw into water,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97877:15"/>of which it is made, and water again eaſily freezeth into Ice; ſo ignorance eaſily diſſolves into vice, and vice as eaſily congeals into ignorance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility, ſpecially of ſpiritual and ſupernatural things. It was ignorance therefore and vice, they were to war againſt, who would endeavour the cure of Souls; and in conſequence to this they were to be armed with vertue and learning. Vertue was the chief; for without true and ſolid vertue, they could never hope that God would make them inſtruments of ſo high a work as the converſion of Souls: nor could they be fit to move others to vertue, unleſs their words were ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by their works, and their exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar life made good their Pulpit-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes: it being moſt certain which the Golden Orator ſaid, that <hi>the beſt Syllogiſm is the Preachers life.</hi> Yet though vertue were the chief agent, ſhe was not to be ingaged without learning for her ſecond. For vertue without learning would not have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority enough to controll malepert ſpirits, and might perhaps degenerate into zeal without diſcretion, and ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97877:16"/>with a good meaning lead to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Both vertue therefore and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were neceſſary for thoſe who ſhould make it their aim by rooting out vice and ignorance, to work the deſired good of Souls.</p>
                     <p>Now, how S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> did lay the foundations which might bring up all that ſhould follow Chriſt in the Society to vertue and learning, we may ſee by what is ſet down in the Conſtitutions of the Society, and is daily practiſed by the Jeſuits: As I ſhall now declare.</p>
                     <p>In the Conſtitutions then the firſt care is, that none be admitted into the Society, who are not of ſuch capacity and diſpoſition that it may juſtly be hoped, that in proceſſe of time they will by Gods grace arrive to ſuch a proportion of learning and vertue, as to become fit to deal with their neighbour for the good of Souls. Upon this account divers are excluded not onely for want of health or other abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, but alſo for ſuch impediments as may give ground to fear the event. For example, thoſe who have been in the world notorious for hainous crimes or infamous lives are excluded the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97877:16"/>unleſs they firſt blot out their ignomy by long and ſerious penance. Becauſe it is not likely that they will have authority ſufficient to handle the Goſpel, who cannot be ſeen in the Pulpit, without memory of their diſgrace. Others again are excluded, becauſe of their violent and refracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry natures, and uncouth diſpoſitions; becauſe, though their abilities promiſe very much, yet it cannot be hoped, that in the many and various actions in which the Society muſt imploy them, they will keep a conſtant te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of vertue, and never laſh out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the exorbitances into which nature doth ſeem to precipitate them. Again, they who have deſerted any religious Order of which they have once worn the habit, though but in their novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate, are excluded the Society: their former inconſtancy prognoſticating a future danger.</p>
                     <p>Now if any that hath no impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment demand to be admitted into the Society, he is asked whether any of the Society ever perſwaded him to this vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and if it be found that any Jeſuit perſwaded him, then he is not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97877:17"/>admitted, but turned back to a new deliberation. For though it be not an ill act to perſwade another, whom we judge fit, to any determinate good courſe of life, yet St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> deſired that the Vocation of all that ſhould ever be admitted into the Society, ſhould proceed wholly from God, and not from man.</p>
                     <p>Theſe cautions are uſed in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of any to the Society. When once they are admitted they are, after a general confeſſion of their paſſed life, trained up to a ſubduing of their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, renouncing themſelves, union with God, and a perfect indifference, that they may be ready to embrace any employment in any place where it ſhall ſeem moſt for the good of Souls to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them, to the greater Glory of God. The time of their probation, which in other Orders is but one year, in the Society is of two years before their Studies, and one year more after their Studies are ended. In the firſt two years they are often tould all the hardſhip they are to expect, ſhewed the Rule, and accuſtomed to the mentall and vocal player, examens, ſpiritual
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97877:17"/>Lectures, and the mortifications which they are daily to practiſe during their whole life, that if they find not in themſelves Strength and reſolution to go on, they may go away in Peace, and take what other courſe they think beſt. But if they continue their good deſires, and give ſatisfaction, then at the end of two years they are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ordinary vowes of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous orders, which are perpetual Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, Chaſtity and Obedience. The exerciſes in which the Novices are practiſed in, and tryed by, are ſerving in Hoſpitals, tending the ſick, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Table, helping the Cook and other menial Officers, going in Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, begging almes from door to door, and the like. All which, being humble actions, practiſe a Man in the myſtery of himſelf, ſubdue pride and ſelf love, and acquaint the Soul with the Croſs of Chriſt. Theſe actions St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> would have all tryed in from the very beginning, and theſe all muſt, and all do daily practiſe in the Houſes of the Society, none at all exempt, but ſuch as ſickneſs exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. This difference only there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97877:18"/>Novices and Antient Fathers; that the Novices have more time for humble exerciſes, as being to get good habits by frequent practiſe. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Fathers (unleſs the neceſſity of their Neighbour do otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) are employed in theſe exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes only, ſo far as to keep up the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Vigour of humility, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, not to take up too much time from their ſtudies or other employments. Yet all are practiſed all their life in humble actions, as ſweeping the houſe, making their beds, ſerving at Table, and the like mean employments.</p>
                     <p>I conceive that many when they read this will admire what it means. They have conceived Idea's of Jeſuits ſo diſtant from theſe actions, that they will ſtand amazed, and either not believe that theſe things are true, or if they believe that I ſay true, (as I am certain that I do) they will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the Jeſuits for them; as deeming theſe actions far below them whom they conceive to be the great Maſters of the World. But to theſe I anſwer that they know not the Grand ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of Chriſts School. Perfection is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97877:18"/>an admirable Fabrick, which reaches as high as Heaven, but unleſs it be built on a profound Renunciation of ones ſelf, 'tis a Vanity, 'tis Hypocriſie, 'tis an empty ſhadow, a lye, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. <hi>He that will follow me ſaith Christ, Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>muſt renounce himſelf.</hi> Eaſie words in reading, but in action the hardeſt in the World, as which contain the whole Enignia of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an perfection, and all the wonders of Religion.</p>
                     <p>If you will know the great myſtery of Jeſuitiſme, of which ſo much hath been falſely blazed in lying Pamphlets, I will tell it you in a word; The myſtery of Jeſuitiſme conſiſteth in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king humble and able men. Here is the ſecret. Theſe ſmall actions, theſe contemptible actions, theſe deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble actions practiſed by Men of good parts, for no other reaſon then for to renounce themſelves in imitation of Chriſt, are the great Engins which raiſe them to the heighth of Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We may reckon many great Men of the Society of Jeſus, who have done great things, and, carrying the Goſpel to the bounds of the Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97877:19"/>have converted many Nations: but where did they lay the foundation of their greatneſs? it was in exerciſing humility, in abnegation of themſelves, in embracing the Croſs of Chriſt which is the ſcience of Saints; If this ſeem ſtrange and unintelligible, I muſt confeſs that it is ſo indeed to thoſe that ſeek Vanity and Worldly Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Quia abſcondiſti haec a ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus &amp; prudentibus &amp; revelasti ea Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulis. Mat.</hi> 11.25. God hath hid theſe things from the wiſe, and ſage of the World, revealed them to little ones.</p>
                     <p>This practiſe therefore of renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our ſelves, St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> would have the continual exerciſe of all his. And leaſt humility through want of a ſure guide might ſwarm from the true path of Charity, he ordained that all the exerciſes done in the time of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, and all the employments after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſhould be ſquared out by obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. By this Obedience every one, renouncing his own will and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, becomes capable of being em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, when, where, and how the Society ſhall judge fitteſt for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97877:19"/>Honour of God. Furthermore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for the diſpoſing of every one right, it is not enough that they be perfectly obedient, but it is alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that the Society do know eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one; therefore doth St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> further order, that every one ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely open his interiour, and all the good and bad of his heart to his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, that ſo every one may be guided and diſpoſed of in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
                     <p>Theſe are the chief means which the Society uſeth in order to attain Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. For the reſt, their life, as to dyet, Lodging, Apparel, is ſuch as beſeems poor Clergy Men: there being nothing of Superfluity allowed, and nothing denyed that is neceſſary.</p>
                     <p>As for faſts and other corporal au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities, there is nothing determined in the rule; only this, that every one ſhall uſe ſuch penance, as his ſuperiour or Spiritual Father, conſidering his health and employments, ſhall judge moſt for his advancement in Spirit. How this point is practiſed in the Society we may judge by reading the acts of thoſe eminent men, whoſe lives are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97877:20"/>writ. As for thoſe that are living, this is true, that the number of thoſe who by Labour and Auſterity do notably impair their Health is very great, which argueth that they rather need a Bridle then a Spur. All this then the Society doth, in order to bring up her Subjects to Solid Vertue. There are yet two things more which do main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conduce to conſerve the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Society in Vigour.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is the power of diſmiſſion; a thing which many carp at, yet which is extreamly advantageous to conſerve the ſociety. <hi>St. Ignatius</hi> therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting, that in a great number of Men, though choſen with all the care, and educated with all the diligence that humane frailty can uſe, divers would in length of time, through wearineſs of labour, or want of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, or ſome of the innumerable ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to which mans life is continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expoſed, become not only uſeleſs to the Society, but alſo noxious, and perhaps ſcandalous too: reflecting on all this, I ſay, St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> did inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute his order ſo, that the vowes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which are made at the end of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97877:20"/>the two years probation, ſhould remain diſpenſable by the General of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. They therefore that in proceſs of time are found by their own fault to become unfit to live in the Society, are diſmiſſed and freed from their Vowes, ſo that if they be not Prieſts (which uſually none are till nine or ten years experience had of them) they may marry, or take what worldly courſe they pleaſe. This they who are diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed cannot complain of; for before they enter they are told of the condition which they undertake, and every half year during their Novice-ſhip, they are particularly asked, whether they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this condition, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with it. <hi>So</hi> they cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, ſince that maxime is manifeſt, <hi>Scienti &amp; volenti non fit injuria.</hi> On the other ſide it is extreamly neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for conſerving the whole ſociety entire to root out thoſe weeds, which if they were let grow would over run the whole Garden of Religion: it is neceſſary to open a Vein and let out the ill blood, before the diſeaſe maſter the whole body; it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſeparate thoſe whoſe contagion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97877:21"/>would like a plague infect all. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick diſorder is the inteſtine Enemy of Religous Houſes, and the bane that hath ruined all thoſe holy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which from Fervent and Illuſtrious beginnings have at length ended in ſmoak and aſhes. This diſorder came not in on a ſuddain, but by little and little, now one, then another relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little of their primitive fervour: Till at length the number of diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſons overtopping the Vertuous, Diſcipline was laid aſide and the rule neglected. This ſad event the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty endeavoureth to foreſtale, by cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the rotten members, before their number and Example corrupt the reſt. I know many have objected againſt this Priviledge of the ſociety; but they have alwayes been anſwered, and the power of diſmiſſion, as often confirmed, as it was queſtioned. In particular. <hi>Greg.</hi> 14. in his Bull of the Year 1591. ſaith, <hi>Eam (potestatem) ratam &amp; intactam eſſe volumus, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam rem magni momenti, ad ſocieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis puritatem &amp; conſervationem reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendam. We will have the power of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſtand Valid, and untouched, as a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97877:21"/>thing of great concern, for the coſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and purity of the Society.</hi> Nor can the Clergy or other Religious Orders complain of this: for in effect as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (not to ſay, more) are diſmiſſed out of other Orders, proportionably great, as out of the ſociety. As it was made appear in the ſeventh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. This is the only difference, that when other Orders diſmiſs thoſe who are incorrigible, and ſcandalous amongſt them, they expell them with the burthen of their Vowes, and ſo they remain Apoſtata's all their Life. The ſociety on the contrary taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that burthen of their Vowes, from all that are diſmiſſed, if they be not profeſſed. Now it very ſeldom happeneth that one who is profeſſed in the ſociety doth deſerve expulſion. For none are profeſſed in the ſociety till many years (ordinarily it is at leaſt 17 or 18 years) experience had of them; all which time if one both give and receive ſatisfaction, it is very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, that after ſo long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he ſhould behave himſelf ſo as to deſerve expulſion from a Religion, in which he hath ſpent ſo great a part of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97877:22"/>his age with content on all ſides.</p>
                     <p>By this means therefore of expulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or diſmiſſion, the ſociety endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth to prevent the miſchief which the imperfection of ſome might in time bring on all; chooſing rather to part with thoſe, from whom ſhe cannot hope any good, than to uſe priſons or corporal chaſtiſements. For ſuch ſeverities (though laudably uſed by other Communities) rather reſtrain the body than the mind, and oftener make men diſſemble their malice, than change their manners.</p>
                     <p>The other thing which in the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will by the grace of God conſerve the whole order in vigour, is, the great caution which is uſed to exclude all manner of ambition of honour and preferments. For all that are profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Society do make a vow, that they will never ſeek neither by direct or indirect means any ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orities, prelacies or dignities, nor ever admit of them when they are offered, unleſs they be commanded by thoſe who can oblige them under ſin. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore they promiſe to detect any of the ſociety whom they ſhall know to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97877:22"/>endeavour directly or indirectly to procure Honours or Dignities. And if any be ever found to have prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in this kind, then is he made ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious, and deprived of Voice Active and Paſſive.</p>
                     <p>This Vow hath many Advantages for conſerving of the true Spirit of the Society. For whereas honour is the moſt ſpecious ſnare of the World, that enchants the mind with moſt powerfull charmes, and proves com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the bane of greateſt Wits, and perſons the beſt qualified; this Vow excludeth all that miſchief, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch a diſtance, or (to uſe the Scripture Phraſe) ſo great a Chaos be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Men of the Society, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, that they cannot arrive or aim at them without wading through Hell it ſelf. It is laudable in other Orders to furniſh the Church with ſo many worthy Prelates, as we ſee they daily do. Yet the Society feareth leaſt by furniſhing others, ſhe ſhould disfurniſh her ſelf; ſhe feareth opening a Gate to honour, leaſt by the ſame Gate ſhe let in ambition, to the diſhonour of the whole Order: ſhe feareth leaſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97877:23"/>thoſe whoſe vertue and learning do chiefly uphold the credit of the Order, and rigour of Diſcipline, might by this means be ſnatcht from her: finally, ſhe feareth leaſt any when by humane frailty they ſhould grow weary of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and relent in fervour, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh their vocation, and ſallyes out by the fair Gate of honour, and under pretence of doing the Church publick ſervice, ſerve their own paſſion. On the contrary, ſhe hopeth that thoſe who really and heartily renounce all thoſe dignities to which their many gallant parts ſeem to make a Bridge, may do the Church more ſervice by continuing in the humility of their own vocation, and by contemning ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, than by accepting it.</p>
                     <p>Thus then is honour bounded out of the Society with the ſtrongeſt ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part that can be, that is by vow. To this we may adde two other things which both aim at the excluſion of all ambition and conſerving humility. The firſt is, that the Government of the Society is not by chapter and plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of voices, which might cauſe factions, and foſter ambition: But all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97877:23"/>Offices are given by the General, or if they be inferiour Offices, by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial: who being informed of the abilities of their ſeveral ſubjects, chooſe whom they think fitteſt, without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting any body with their deſign till the Election be paſt. The other is, that in the Society there is a perfect equality between all; no man for birth, or learning, or antiquity, or any thing elſe hath any advantage of place, diet, cloathing, lodging, or the like. But all ſhare alike, and take their turns in the meaneſt Offices, none being exempt. All this conſidered, I do not know how it is poſſible practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſpeaking to exclude ambition out of any Community, more than it is out of the Society.</p>
                     <p>Theſe be the chief means by which the Society endeavoureth to educate her ſubjects to vertue, and keep up the primitive vigour of the Order.</p>
                     <p>Now for learning, which as I ſaid in the beginning of this Chapter, was the ſecond thing whereby men of the Society were to be made fit inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for their end. The eſteem which <hi>St. Ignatius</hi> made of learning, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97877:24"/>evidenced in the great labour he took himſelf in ſtudies, as I have already ſhewed. And in the Society he deſired to wedde Learning to Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſo ſtrongly as that they ſhould never be divorced. For this reaſon he ordered that none ſhould be profeſſed of four vows in the Society (which is the degree of thoſe that are the chief) who had not got to ſuch a pitch in Sciences, as that they were by ſworn Examiners judged able to teach Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy and Divinity with applauſe. Though notwithſtanding, for avoiding of honours, he would not have the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Society take the title of Doctor, but where it ſhould be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. For the ſtudies of the Society this may be ſaid in general, that they embrace no ſtudy by which they may not hope to become more ſerviceable to the Church for the good of their neighbour; and they refuſe none, by which they may hope to become more ſerviceable. In particular they all are taught, firſt humanity, if they be not well entered before their admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Then they ſtudy Philoſophy and Mathematicks for three years.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97877:24"/>Laſtly for the ſpace of four years, they ſtudy their Divinity; and with that they hear a leſſon of H. Scripture, and another of Hebrew in order to the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding of holy writ. Theſe are their ſtudies, wherein they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue at leaſt ſeven years; during which time they are often practiſed in preaching, that they may get ſome facility, and that every ones talent may be ſeen. And to ſecure the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitance, which wits may eaſily fall into, the rule ſpeaketh plain, that none muſt broach new opinions, or teach any thing which is not confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to what the Catholick Church holdeth, and approved Authors teach. And of this even before their admittance they are warned, and not admitted unleſs they reſolve to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. Which <hi>I</hi> take notice of, to ſhew how groundleſs their cavils are who object Novell opinions and exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Doctrine to the Society, whereas no ſuch Doctrine either is or can be tolerated among them. After their ſtudies they go to the third year of Probation where they endeavour by frequent Prayer and Meditation to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97877:25"/>wholly to the ſtudy and practiſe of ſolid Vertue, according to the end and inſtitute of the Society, re-aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming for that purpoſe the ſame expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, wherewith they were tryed in their firſt Probation or Novice-ſhip. And this is what the Society doth, for to make her own Subjects fit for thoſe functions which they are afterwards to undertake for the good of their Neighbours.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CAP. III.</hi> What they of the Society do in order to help their Neighbour, for the good of Souls.</head>
                     <p>AFter that the Fathers of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety have ended their ſtudies and Probations, and now are by Gods grace furniſhed with ſuch Talents of learning and Vertue, as every one hath been able to arrive unto, the firſt thing that they are to expect is, to be prefently ſet on work, and kept in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97877:25"/>employment, that idleneſs which St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> calleth the Origin and root of all evill, <hi>otium malorum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium origo,</hi> may have no place amongſt them.</p>
                     <p>Now their employments, which they undertake for their Neighbour, are various. The firſt (for I will begin from thence, according to the courſe of Mans age) is teaching the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme or Chriſtian Doctrine. This employment St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> eſteemed ſo much, that beſides commending it with his own example even when he was General of the Society, he would alſo command it, and exact, that all that were profeſſed of the Society ſhould by a ſpecial Vow promiſe to God, to have a peculiar care of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Catechiſme. Further he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that all that were imployed in the Government of the Society, ſhould at the entrance of their office, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe the children and ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for a good number of dayes. As St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo St. <hi>Francis Xaverius</hi> in the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this holy exerciſe, both by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and precept, as the moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97877:26"/>and which he uſed to call, <hi>His employment.</hi> He never let a day ſlip, when poſſible he could, without cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing: and he uſed to go about the ſtreets, to call all the children, and ſervants, and ſlaves together to hear the Chriſtian Doctrine. When he went to <hi>Japony,</hi> he left <hi>Gaſpar Barraeus</hi> Superiour of the Society in his place, and gave him this inſtruction, that he ſhould himſelf perſonally Catechiſe, and not commit that charge to any elſe; whereas in other things he left him free to uſe the help of others when he ſhould think fit. And in effect thoſe Wonderfull converſions of ſo many Nations as he became Apoſtle of, are the fruits of Catechiſme. Nor is it to be wondred that the Society ſets ſo much by teaching the Catechiſme. 'Tis the Doctrine of Chriſt, that which the Son of God taught with word, with example, with Signs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies. 'Tis the way to eternal Life, and as they call it in the Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> the ſcience of Heaven, the only know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge neceſſary to Salvation. 'Tis the ſtudy which moſt imports the World; for thoſe that now are chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97877:26"/>will within a few years be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of all the World; if therefore they be well inſtructed now, you may hope of good plants good trees, and good fruit of good ſeed: on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary neglect theſe Children now, and you ſhall ſoon have an unruly, licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſavage Nation.</p>
                     <p>For theſe reaſons and many others the ſociety ſaith with Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.14. <hi>Sinite parvulos venire ad me, let little ones come to me;</hi> and maketh this the firſt of her cares to inſtruct little ones, and ignorant people in the Chriſtian Doctrine. With what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs they perform this, I had rather you ſhould hear from an Extern, then from one of the ſociety. <hi>Laurence Beyerlinke,</hi> then a Canon of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> that died not very long ſince, a man of great Learning, as his books teſtifie, writeth thus in <hi>Theat. vitae Humanae Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>lib. C.</hi> 
                        <q>In our age, among all that profeſs Religion, thoſe of the ſociety of Jeſus do with great diligence and great fruit apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to catechiſing youth. If there were nothing elſe, this might make them commendable to all, that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97877:27"/>with ſo great zeal, and ſo exact a method, they do a thing ſo advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to the Church of God. It ſeemeth to be the proper function of the Jeſuits to which they all ſet themſelves, endeavouring ſo to form the minds of little ones, that they may ſuck Chriſtian piety with their milk. By this means it happeneth that in the Towns where the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety reſides, you ſhall ſee the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren mannerly and devout, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcourſe of thoſe things, which in other places the elder are ignorant of. Nor do the Jeſuits take this pains with the children of the rich only, but even with the pooreſt Tradeſmen, even with almes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and beggars. All theſe they inſtruct whenſoever on Feſtival dayes they can get them together. Nor do they ſtop within the Walls of Cities, but make excurſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to thoſe Pariſhes where Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours are wanting to their duty. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtle, they become all to all, and accomodate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the manners of all, to teach all. In <hi>Antwerp</hi> alone you
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97877:27"/>ſhall ſee ſometimes thirty Fathers and more employed in this pious work.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>The next imployment, following the courſe of mans age, is the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Humanity, that is, the Latine and Greek tongues in ſeveral Claſſes or Schools of Grammar, Syntax, Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Rhetorick. In theſe they endeavour to educate Youth to learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, as all along to inſtill piety. This is a thing which the Society hath alwaies practiſed from her firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that (as <hi>Greg.</hi> 13. ſaith in his Bull <hi>Aedificandi,</hi>) <hi>by divine voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> In every Colledge of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, you have five or ſix Maſters em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in teaching theſe lower ſchools. What labour and toyle theſe men muſt devoure you may eaſily gueſſe if You reflect, what it is for a man that hath otherwiſe good talents, to conſume his age with children. How many impertinencies muſt he ſtrive with, that is content to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>find to the company of little one. He muſt ſpur on one, bridle another, bear with the rudeneſs of this, wink at the paſſion of that, controul the malepert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97877:28"/>of t'other, and ſtudy the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of all, to win all to vertue and learning. A great labour, and if it were not undertaken for Gods ſake, <hi>I</hi> ſhould call it intollerable. But ſince it doth advantage the good of Souls ſo much, it is embraced by all the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety with a great deal of fervour, without pretending any gain, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing capable of receiving any ſalary for their pains, but only what God hath laid up in the other World, for thoſe that labour in his Vineyard. Twenty two Years <hi>Turcelline</hi> taught theſe low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſchools, <hi>Cerda</hi> 30. and <hi>John Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> 40 years together, and very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have and do ſpend all their dayes in teaching little children. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety hath only the labour, others reap the fruit. In theſe ſchools are formed thoſe who afterwards become Religious in Cloyſters, Preachers in Pulpits, Paſtours in Churches, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in Armies, Judges in Courts. All the Cities wherein the Society is ſee this ſo well, that generally the chief motive why they deſire Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges is, that their children may be taught that piety and learning which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97877:28"/>may make them fit to manage greater affairs afterward. The number of their ſchollars as <hi>Contern</hi> gueſſeth was in the year 1618 one hundred and fifty thouſand; another ſince hath counted them to be above two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. Another in his book <hi>de Instit. Chriſt. pueritiae</hi> ſaith, that if the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety had been from the beginning foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for this alone, to teach youth, and did only this one thing, yet would this alone give the Society credit and ſplendour enough, and adminiſter to them in teaching matter enough of of vertue, and to the whole World of profit.</p>
                     <p>The third employment wherein the Society endeavoureth to help their neighbour is, (to go on in Doctrinal matters) teaching the higher ſchools, as Philoſophy, Mathematicks, and the ſeveral parts of Divinity, both poſitive and ſpeculative. Theſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies commend themſelves enough by their name and nature. For Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick beſides the profit, is the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanteſt of all ſtudies; Philoſophy ſerves for nothing elſe then to ſtrengthen reaſon, and diſcuſſe nature; Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97877:29"/>is the bulwark of the Church and School of Faith. In theſe ſtudies the Society laboureth to perfect men in the beſt part of nature (that is reaſon) and Chriſtians in the knowledg of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural things; that they may be ſecure in the wayes both of time and eternity. I need not ſay any thing of the ſucceſſe which the ſociety hath had in theſe, and in their other ſtudies. I will only uſe the words of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 10.38. <hi>Operibus credite, believe their works.</hi> Look on their innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble learned works; look on the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſciences illuſtrated by them; look on the Catalogue of the books made by the Society in the firſt hundred years, which Catalogue makes a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Tome; and let their works ſpeak for them. I know ſome have carped at ſome of their works, but withall I know the repute which the Society hath got in all manner of learning is ſuch, that I appeal to the judgment of their adverſaries, and deſire no commendation but what they do give them.</p>
                     <p>The fourth employment is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and explicating holy Scripture in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97877:29"/>the Pulpit for the edification of the people. This is that function to which all other ſciences ſerve; the end and terme of all. By this they labour to ſpread the Goſpel of Chriſt, and teach the way of perfection, not to little ones, and ignorant people, but to thoſe who are, or ſhould be grown up to a manhood in perfection. For the manner of preaching three things are ſet down in the firſt Tome of the Hiſt. of the Society l. 2. which from the beginning the preachers of the Society ſet themſelves for inviolable precepts, according to which afterwards their rules were drawn. The firſt is that for the matter of their Sermons they ſhould, omitting obſcure and curious queſtions, inſiſt chiefly on thoſe things which contain Chriſtian duty, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate vice, and plant vertue. The ſecond that they ſhould never affect an empty verbal eloquence, nor ſtudy quaint termes, but ſolid truthes and eternal verities, which they ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate with a fervour expreſſed in their eyes, voice, countenance, and geſture. Laſtly that remembring that thoſe preachers were moſt efficacious
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97877:30"/>who brought their own example for inſtance of what they ſaid, they ſhould live ſo, that their whole life might continually preach all that they taught in the pulpit. Theſe are the rules of their Preachers, by obſerving which they have and do dayly through Gods grace work great effects.</p>
                     <p>The fifth employment enters farther into the interior of mens ſouls. It conſiſteth in adminiſtring the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſpecially of confeſſion and communion. The frequenting theſe two Sacraments was the exerciſe of the primitive Church, as <hi>Coccius</hi> and divers learned authors prove. And for confeſſion, beſides thoſe places wherein power is given to prieſts to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſins, we have <hi>Act.</hi> 19. v. 18. <hi>that many of the believers did come</hi> (to <hi>Paul</hi> and his companions) <hi>announcing their acts,</hi> or as the Syriack hath it, <hi>offenſas ſuas,</hi> their offences. For the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion we have the expreſſe text of <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42. <hi>They were perſevering in the communion of breaking of bread;</hi> which all antiquity ever underſtood, as likewiſe modern Authours do, of fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent communion. This was their
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97877:30"/>practice, and whilſt this practice laſted their fervour was ſuch, as after ages have ever admired. But in ſucceſſe of time impiety ſo perverted mens mindes, that they grew to love their ſins and hate the remedies. Before the Society was inſtituted, as <hi>Florimond</hi> and divers authors tell, it was a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to frequent the Sacraments; but <hi>St. Ignatius</hi> and his reſtored this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive cuſtome of the Church. For this reaſon the Learned Cardinal <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius,</hi> who had ſeen what was the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the World ſometime before, and a long time after the Society was erected, uſed to call the Jeſuites church at <hi>Rome, Anaſtaſia,</hi> that is, <hi>Reſurgens, Riſing,</hi> becauſe that in that place he ſaid he ſeemed to ſee the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick church riſe out of the Lethurgy of ſin to a new vigour, by frequenting theſe two ſo wholeſome ſacraments. Indeed it is wonderful to ſee what ſtrange concourſe there is now a daies in all catholick countries to theſe two Sacraments; churches are filled, and the confeſſors are fain to fit all the day long in their ſeats; and that not at Eaſter only, or once or twice a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97877:31"/>year, but upon all the great feaſts. In particular it is remarkable how thoſe daies uſually conſecrated to debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I mean <hi>Shrovetide,</hi> are now ſpent in Catholick countries. For where there is a Colledge of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, there is alwaies at that time a general communion, to which all are by precedent ſermons invited. And they come ſo faſt, that in great Towns they reckon the communicants by thouſands. In ſome cities there have been counted twenty, in ſome thirty, in ſome fourty thouſand, that in one <hi>Shrovetide</hi> have received the holy Euchariſt in the church of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
                     <p>The ſixt employment is the giving the ſpiritual Exerciſe; which becauſe it is almoſt unknown in <hi>England</hi> even to moſt catholicks, I muſt explicate it. The ſpiritual exerciſe then is a retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in which the Excercitant with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawes himſelf for ſome number of daies from all communication with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in order to attend to converſe with God, and his own ſoul in prayer. In this retirement divers meditations are given and ſeveral inſtructions (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodated
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97877:31"/>by an experienced ghoſtly Father to every one) whereby the ſoul is lead to a knowledg of her ſelf, a deceſtation of her ſins, a love of God and imitation of Chriſt. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe ſpiritual Exerciſes do moſt ſpecially help the ſoul is, to make a good election, and ſettle well the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture life of every one according to his own vocation. Theſe ſpiritual exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes were compounded by St. <hi>Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and (which is wonderful) in the firſt year of his converſion. <hi>I</hi> may juſtly call them the chief ſecret of the Society, the fountain from whence they ſuck the Spirit of God, and the channel by which they derive the ſame Spirit into others. <hi>Ludovicus Strado</hi> of the holy Order of St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> had tryed the ſpiritual exerciſes, and he called them <hi>Tyrocinium totius mundi,</hi> the Noviciate of all the world; becauſe in them every one may learn to ſteer the whole courſe of his life to perfection, according to each ones ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral calling. And <hi>Auguſtine Carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jal,</hi> of the Order of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> after having laboured in the <hi>West Indies,</hi> after having undergone with commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97877:32"/>divers Offices in <hi>Spain,</hi> after having viſited the Monaſteries of his Order in <hi>Italy,</hi> by the authority of his Holyneſſe, at length in the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of St. <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Bononia,</hi> made for the ſpace of a moneth the ſpiritual Exerciſes in the year 1601, and he gave this teſtimony of them, <hi>That from the time he was firſt a Religious man he had alwaies wiſhed to find out a way by which he might walk straight to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and that now at length in theſe ſpiritual Exerciſes he had found out that way.</hi> Laſtly that great Maſter of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, great preacher, and great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templative <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Granada,</hi> of the Order of St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> ſpeaketh of theſe ſpiritual Exerciſes thus, <hi>So much ſpiritual Doctrine did I learn in thoſe Exerciſes and Documents, that my whole life can not ſuffice to write what there God ſhewed me.</hi> Thus do theſe great men ſpeak: and this <hi>I</hi> may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to add, that what skill ſoever the Society hath in helping ſouls, what dexterity ſoever they ſhew in diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſpirits, what zeal ſoever they burn with for the good of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, all that they owe to theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97877:32"/>which form in them the true Spirit of the Society, enlighten their mindes, and inflame their hearts. It is not therefore without great reaſon that they retire themſelves every year to make theſe Exerciſes, nor can they be condemned if they commend that to others which they find ſo beneficial to themſelves. Many do retire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Colledges of the Society to make theſe ſpiritual exerciſes, and none ever repented himſelf of his pains; but all ever acknowledged, that the fruit which by this means redounds to their ſoul, is greater then they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver could expect, or can expreſs.</p>
                     <p>The ſeventh employment which the Society undertakes for the good of their neighbour is, to help in Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, comfort the ſick, relieve the poor, and impriſoned perſons, firſt for their ſpiritual, then for their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral aſſiſtance alſo. Thoſe that know the Society and are acquainted with their Colledges and Houſes, can tell you how aſſiduous the Jeſuites are in theſe kinds of charities. If there be an Hoſpital in any Town where the Jeſuites reſide, they alwaies depute
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97877:33"/>ſome of their Colledges, to aſſiſt, the ſick there; for to catechiſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them; for to adminiſter the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments to them, for to beg almes if need require up and down the town for them; and when ſervants are want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for to tend the ſick, ſweep the chambers, make their beds, provide them neceſſaries. In like manner where there is a priſon they go very often to comfort thoſe poor ſouls, to encourage and aſſiſt them (if they be condemned) to a good chriſtian death, or, if their crimes be not capital, to aid them in what they can, ſo to win them to ſerious repentance, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of their life. As for other poor ſick and diſtreſſed perſons, they ſeek them up and down in their ſtreets and houſes, counting it a fault if any ſuffer whom they can relieve. This is yet more admirable, in the time of contagious Diſeaſes and Plagues. Whenſoever that happeneth in any place where the Society is, preſently a proportionable number of Fathers are expoſed for the aſſiſtance of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; theſe Fathers are choſen out of thoſe who voluntarily offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97877:33"/>a ſacrifice to God for the Good of their Neighbour. For it is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Society, that when there is any great occaſion of a hard duty for the good of Souls, the Rector or Superior calleth all his Subjects toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and acquainting them with the urgent neceſſity, deſireth them firſt to commend the matter to God, and then that thoſe who find in themſelves a deſire to be expoſed, and are ready to lay down their life for their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſhould after a convenient deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration acquaint him with their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. Out of thoſe then that offer themſelves the Superiour chooſeth whom he thinketh fit; and theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly are very able men, for the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour cannot think it fit to expoſe novices or imperfect perſons to ſo great danger. This is what was pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed in the beginning of the Society, and (thanks be to God) this practice is as much in vigour at this day as ever it was. None even of the enemies of the ſociety can ſay, that in the towns where the Jeſuits live, either priſons or Hoſpitals, or poor, or infected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are neglected by them. Though
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97877:34"/>notwithſtanding this practiſe coſts the Society the loſs of many brave and gallant Men. In <hi>Gant</hi> in the year 1633 the Dutch Colledge loſt in four moneths ten, who ſucceſſively ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed themſelves to help the infected of the plague, all of them very able Men. At <hi>Berges</hi> neer <hi>Dunkerke</hi> they loſt five on the ſame account in three moneths. In the year 1649 in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious feaver at <hi>Rome,</hi> beſides di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, the General of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety <hi>F. Vincent Caraffa</hi> aſſiſting the ſick, contracted the diſeaſe and died.</p>
                     <p>And to come home here in <hi>London,</hi> in the laſt great plague, three of the Society were expoſed to the aſſiſtance of thoſe that were infected. One of them was <hi>F. Henry Mors,</hi> who got the infection but recovered, and was afterward in the time of the long Parliament executed at <hi>Tyburn</hi> for a Prieſt and Jeſuit. So God diſpoſed that his charitable labours ſhould at length be crowned with a glorious death.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> conceive the Reader will be no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle aſtoniſhed at this Superlative chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. A charity ſo great that none
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97877:34"/>would dare to command it, did not very Zealous Men Voluntarily offer it, and even beg to be admitted to it. To adventure ones life for to aſſiſt poor Miſcreants that can not render you thanks, to run into loathſome priſons and ſtinking Hoſpitals, to attend Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerous and naſty ſickneſſes, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thoſe that have the plague, and all this for no other fee but only the conſcience of doing a good work, pleaſing to God, and profitable to our Neighbour, is a charity ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent, that I ſhould fear that none would believe it, had I not all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions abroad for witneſſes of what I ſay, and every Town wherein there is a Colledge of the Society to atteſt the truth of it.</p>
                     <p>The eighth employment which the Society undertaketh for their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is that which is called Miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. All that I have hitherto ſaid is practiſed within the boſome of the Catholick church. This extendeth it ſelf to the furtheſt bounds of the Earth, to Pagans and Heathens, and ſeeking wayes to dilate the knowledge of Chriſt, undergoeth, beſides all the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97877:35"/>labours already mentioned, a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual baniſhment from friends, from country, from all the comforts of life. Theſe Miſſions were begun by S. <hi>Francis Xaverius,</hi> who, at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>John</hi> the Third King of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> was ſent into the Eaſt <hi>Indies.</hi> And admirable man, whoſe zeal ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted the flames of the torrid zone, whoſe conquering mind overcame the untamed Ocean, whoſe vaſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was of a larger circumference then the whole univerſe. Danger was his delight, labour his ſolace, and death his prize. If I ſhould tell you what he hath done for the church of of God I muſt name all the chief countries and towns of the Eaſt, for all of them he illuſtrated with the light of the Goſpel. The Son doth not make ſo great a change in the World, when it draws it out of the ſhade wherein night had buried it, as this gallant ſoul did in all the Eaſt, which he drew out of the Egyptian darkneſs of infidelity to the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble light of Chriſtianity.</p>
                     <p>After this great Apoſtles example many thouſand of the Society have
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97877:35"/>gone, and do daily go to ſpread the Goſpel of Chriſt in all the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the World: To Eaſt, and Weſt, <hi>India, China, Japony, Braſile, Paraquaria, Canada, Peru, Mexico, Chili, Abaſſia, Congo, Mauritania, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomotapa,</hi> and in a word to the known Nations of the unknown World. So that the Society may without vanity ſay
<q>Quae regio in terris noſtri non plena labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris?</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>If the Society heareth of a way opened into any country of the World, where Chriſt is not known, preſently they offer themſelves to go thither. They know they are to paſs through cruell and mercileſs ſeas, to more cruell and mercileſs Nations. They know they are to travers vaſt woods and deſarts full of Lions and Tigers; to find out a people more ſavage then thoſe Beaſts. They know they are to climbe over Mountains of Snow and Ice, to find out men colder then ice, all frozen in impiety; all this they know, and they weigh all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97877:36"/>the labour and danger they muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, yet nothing can ſtop them. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was there yet labour or danger found ſo great, but that the Society (through the aſſiſtance of God) found greater minds to encounter and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thoſe labours and dangers, whereſoever the good of ſouls did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire their help. This is a truth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to all this habitable World; there being no country known to Men, where the Society doth not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for Chriſt. But all this is done with incredible pains. Weary jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies by ſea and Land, perpetual drudgery, tedious ſickneſſes without comfort of Doctour or Phyſick, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely, and many times violent death, are daily and hourly to be expected by thoſe that will labour to inſtruct wild Men and Cannibals, and manure them to the Faith of Chriſt. And all theſe troubles and dangers are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled by the want of thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts which Friends, and acquaintance, and kindred, and the civility and plenty of <hi>Europe</hi> afford. So that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever goeth into theſe Miſſions of the Society, muſt make account, that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97877:36"/>he leapeth into a furnace of perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al tribulation, where he is never to ceaſe labouring and induring for Chriſt, till with his laſt breath he is ſacrificed to Divine love. Yet ſuch is the mercy of God, that the Society wanteth not men, who voluntarily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace all this fatigue, and willingly offer themſelves, and beg theſe Miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                     <p>Theſe are then the employments of the Society, theſe their functions: for I omit the Naval and Camp miſſions, wherein the Society endeavoureth to aſſiſt ſeamen, and Souldiers; <hi>I</hi> omit their frequent endeavours to reconcile thoſe that are at Enmity: <hi>I</hi> omit their induſtry in promoting of Plety by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalities and other wayes; all which may in ſome ſort be gueſſed at, by what <hi>I</hi> have already ſaid. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude then this chapter, I deſire the Reader to reflect on one thing, which will much inhance the price of all theſe actions. It is that all this is done <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> The Jeſuits do not expect any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, nor can they receive any ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, or recompence for their pains in teaching, preaching, helping the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97877:37"/>ſick, adminiſtring Sacraments, or any of the charitable functions which they embrace. But as they do frankly and freely, for the honour of God, whatſoever they can do for the good of their Neighbour, ſo they rely on the Providence of God who exciteth devout people to ſupply their neceſſity out of pure charity. This they do not do as condemning the Clergy and Religious, who take Tithes and Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends for their ſpiritual functions juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the church alloweth them: but they deſire to imitate as neer as they can their Bleſſed Saviour, who though he lived on the almes, which devout people gave him, yet did freely and without thought of recompence, all that his eternal Father ordained him to do. By this means on the one ſide they avoid all ſemblance of Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and ſimony, and on the other ſide the people, whom lucre often times makes nigards to God, and ſtrangers to the ſacraments, are ſooner wone to do good, when they ſee it coſts them nothing, but a good will, to make uſe of the ſocieties labour in ſchooles, in ſermons, in ſacraments,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97877:37"/>and the reſt of their ſpiritual and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable functions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CAP. IV.</hi> Whence it comes that the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety is still perſecuted and calumnied by many.</head>
                     <p>ONe would think that ſo many charitable actions, done purely for love, might deſerve a reciprocal love: and that men who haraſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with continual toyle for the profit of others, ſhould at leaſt reap thanks for their pains, and find com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in their travail, not indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; comfort, not perſecution. Yet on the contrary, of the ſociety we may ſay as of the Primitive church, <hi>notum est nobis quia ubique contradici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ei,</hi> we know that every where they are contradicted and perſecuted. But this oppoſition is not ſo generall as it is noyſed; if the adverſaries of the Jeſuits be many, their friends are alſo many, and they of the abler and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97877:38"/>better ſort of people: as evidently appeareth by this, that though the Enemies of the ſociety do all that they can poſſibly to overthrow them, yet notwithſtanding the Jeſuits are ſtill maintained, and honoured where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Catholick Religion is allowed.</p>
                     <p>Three ſorts of Men <hi>I</hi> obſerve in <hi>England</hi> to be adverſaries of the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. The firſt and worſt of all are ſome Catholicks, who have ſuch a tooth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Jeſuits that they cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them one good word. Theſe are unexcuſable, for ſince they know the Catholick Church hath approved the inſtitute of the ſociety, and they take that Church for their infallible guide, they can have no colour for condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſociety. They do the ſociety great wrong, but themſelves far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (ſpecially ſome of them whoſe quality is ſuch that they ought to be more exemplar) for in effect, whilſt they endeavour to diſgrace the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety they defame themſelves. They muſt think their Auditours very igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in Chriſtian duty, if they ſuppoſe them ſuch as cannot reflect what ſin detraction is. Some of theſe would ſeem
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97877:38"/>Zealots, and they have ſomething that might give them vogue enough, if en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and this ſpirit of detraction did not de-ingrate all the reſt. Theſe <hi>I</hi> would deſire to meditate on that of St. <hi>John,</hi> Epiſt. 1. c. v. 20. <hi>Si quis dixerit, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam diligo Deum, &amp; fratrem ſuum ode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, mendax eſt. If any body ſay, I love God, and yet hateth his Brother, he is a lyar.</hi> Again I would deſire them to reflect on the ſevere cenſures which they incur by ſpeaking againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the Society, which is no leſs then Excommunication <hi>ipſo facto;</hi> as appeareth by the Bull of <hi>Greg.</hi> 13. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning <hi>Aſcendente Domino,</hi> Dated 1584. Where he hath theſe words, <hi>Praecipimus in virtute ſanctae obedientiae ac ſub poenis excommunicationis latae ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae, nec non inhabilitatis ad quaevis officia &amp; beneficia ſaecularia, &amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumvis ordinum regularia, eo ipſo abſque alia declaratione incurrendis (quarum abſolutionem nobis &amp; ſucceſſoribus noſtris reſervamus) ne quis cujuscunque ſtatus, gradus, &amp; praeeminentiae exiſtat dictae ſocietatis inſtitutum, aut constitutiones quovis diſputandi vel etiam veritatis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagandae quaeſito colore, directe vel indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97877:39"/>impugnare vel eis contradicere au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat. We command in vertue of Holy Obedience, and under pain of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> latae ſententiae, <hi>as alſo of ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to any office or benefice ſecular or regular, to be incurred without further declaration, and from which they cannot be abſolved but by us or our ſucceſſors, That no man of what ſtate degree or emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence ſoever he be dare to impugne or contradict the Inſtitute of the ſociety or conſtitutions; either directly or indirectly under any colour of diſputing or ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the truth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Another ſort of men there are who hate the Jeſuites becauiſe they will, never reflecting why; Theſe are a malevolent ſort of men, whoſe laviſh tongues vent nothing but cenſures, their zeal is fury, their devotion miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, their envious ſouls are never lodg'd at eaſe, but in the ruine of their Neighbours. <hi>Root and Branch.</hi> was the word wherewith they deſign'd all the Papiſts long ſince to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Cruel ſpirits, that could rejoyce whilſt they warm'd themſelves at the fire which conſumed their King and Country: as though their Govenant
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97877:39"/>had been made with death and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Aristides</hi> was a gallant man, as moſt that ever <hi>Athens</hi> ſaw, a great Oratour, and great Commander, and ſo upright in all his dealings that he was ſirnamed the <hi>Just.</hi> Yet no vertue could give him ſecurity, nor ſcreen him from envy. The people, inſtigated by certain hotſpurs, would needs have him baniſhed. To their Oſtraciſme therefore they went to vote <hi>Ariſtides</hi> out of their Republick. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtides</hi> went along with them, and whilſt he was on the ſhoreſide, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the fury of the people more mercileſſe then the waves of the ſea, one comes to him with a ſhell (for in ſhells they writ their ſentence, which thence was called Oſtraciſme) and deſires him to write in it the word for baniſhing <hi>Ariſtides. Ariſtides</hi> ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the man, asked him friendly whether he knew <hi>Ariſtides;</hi> not I, quoth the man; And why then muſt he be baniſhed! ſaith <hi>Aristides,</hi> what have you againſt him? He is juſt (ſaith the fellow) he is called Juſt, that name I hate, we are reſolved, he ſhall be gone; pray write: <hi>So Ariſtides</hi>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97877:40"/>writ as the man deſired, and though not without indignation, yet was he glad to ſee that his crime was Juſtice. This furious ſot was a picture of many miſ-ſhaped ſouls that we have in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> They do not know what a Jeſuite is, they cannot tell that ever they ſaw a Jeſuit, they cannot name any one true crime committed by any Jeſuit, yet they hate the very name, nor ſhall any perſwade them to reaſon. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hope much of theſe ſpirits, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I conceive many of them were miſled by thoſe incendiaries of our late inteſtine wars, who from the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits painted the King a Papiſt, the Pope a Monſter, and the Jeſuites his horns, I will not diſpair, but that now, when thoſe Apoſtles of Hell are ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, theſe men may be brought ſo far, as to reſolve not to be enemies to the Jeſuites till they can tell why, which is all I beg of them.</p>
                     <p>A third ſort of men there are who are adverſaries of the ſociety of Jeſus, not out of malice, but prevented by a prejudicate opinion. Theſe are, the rational Proteſtants. They have heard much againſt the Jeſuites, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them. So they preſume
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97877:40"/>that the crimes objected, are by ſilence allowed. It is to theſe particularly that I conſecrate this Treatiſe. And as I have ſhewed them in the three pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Chapters what is the end of the ſociety, and what the means they uſe to perfect themſelves and help their neighbours; ſo now I intend to ſhew them whence it comes that the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety is ſo much maligned; and in the following chapters I will anſwer the Objections made againſt the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                     <p>The firſt and principal reaſon that occurreth to me is Gods eternal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, who, fince all was (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh) wrapt up in ſin, hath reſolved to make uſe of the perverſneſs of the wicked for the tryal of the good; and hath fixed this irrevocable decree, 2 <hi>ad Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Omnes qui volunt pie vivere in Christo Jeſu, perſecutionem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientur; all that will live piouſly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi> So the Confeſſors, ſo the Martyrs, ſo the Apoſtles, ſo Chriſt himſelf found it. We muſt not therefore expect, that the Jeſuites ſhall be more kindly uſed by the World then Chriſt and his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97877:41"/>Saints were. <hi>Si mundus vosodit, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tote quia me priorem vobis odio habuit. If the world hate you, ſaith Christ, Joh.</hi> 15.18. to thoſe that follow him, <hi>know that they bated me before you.</hi> They that carry the name of Jeſus muſt not be aſhamed to carry alſo the croſſe of Jeſus. Nor muſt they expect, that for them, either God ſhould change his Decrees, or the world its nature.</p>
                     <p>'Tis the will of God, that the juſt ſhould be perſecuted, and 'tis the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the World to hate Juſtice. The plurality of Votes in this World al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies goes for pleaſure and profit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt learning and vertue. 'Tis a wretchedneſs in men to do ſo, but it is an unſpeakable ſecret of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, to make uſe of this wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of men, for to perfect his ſaints. This God did do with the primitive church, this he did with the Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Saint <hi>Benedict,</hi> St. <hi>Dominick, St. Francis,</hi> and the reſt, and this he doth with the ſociety. And <hi>I</hi> take it for an argument of Gods great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will to the ſociety, that he is pleaſed to try them by adverſity. This <hi>I</hi> am further convinced of, when I reflect,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97877:41"/>that all their perſecutions have ſtill ended to their advantage, which ſheweth the ſecret hand of God that directs all for their good, and makes it an argument of the Jeſuites perfection that they thrive by perſecution, as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> did the primitive Church, to the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of all the World. Surely there hath been enough done to exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the Jeſuites out of <hi>England,</hi> and out of all the World, if God did not maintain them. But as long as God maintaineth them, perſecution ſhall only perfect, not overthrow them.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond reaſon why the Jeſuites have many adverſaries <hi>I</hi> take from the nature of their functions. To teach and inſtruct others, is a thing very profitable, but not very pleaſing. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions which maſters muſt uſe are neceſſary, but odious, and many times children remember more what they ſuffered, then what they got in ſchools. In a hundred or two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand ſcholars, ſome will be uncapable of learning, others unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and of no application: Yet theſe many times are of great birth, and prove leading men in towns, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and armies. Now when it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97877:42"/>(as often it muſt do) that any of theſe are checked, and corrected, and perhaps (when they are incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible) expulſed the ſchools, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains an adverſary for the ſociety, as great as any of theſe may chance to be in birth or dignity. All this on the Jeſuites ſide is unavoydable, for if you will keep ſchools, you muſt keep order and diſcipline, and correct thoſe that tranſgreſſe. Nor on the other ſide muſt we wonder, that ſome without any offence prove ungrateful. Moſt men are ſo to God and to Chriſt; what if ſome be ſo to the Jeſuits? What <hi>I</hi> have ſaid of ſchools, is in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to be underſtood of the other employments of the ſociety. A prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher muſt reprehend vice, he muſt ſpeak home to his auditour. And how many are there ſo lew'd, that they hate the commendation of chaſtity? how many ſo riotous that they cannot endure an invective againſt drinking? how many are netled when they hear exceſſe in apparrel condemned? <hi>I</hi> know where it happened that a Biſhop was ready to inform againſt a Jeſuit, as having ſpoken treaſon, when he
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97877:42"/>had preached againſt vanity in apparel. And the complaint had been carried to court, had not the chief Magiſtrates of the town, teſtifyed that the good Father had ſaid nothing which might any wayes touch upon the State, and further that they themſelves had deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Father to preach of that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as not being able to bear the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence which their Wives and Children put them to for their apparel. But reprehenſion is a touchy matter, and no warineſſe is enough to prevent complaints. In like manner a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſarius</hi> muſt not flatter his penitent; he muſt urge reſtitution of goods and fame, he muſt be ſatisfied that the purpoſe of amendment is real, he muſt ſee the contrition be hearty and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. Theſe are no pleaſing actions, and many finding the Society more rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then they could wiſh, fling off, and call the Jeſuites ſcrupulous, and Puritant-papiſts, though the Jeſuites and the Puritans be <hi>antipodes</hi> in all their life and maximes.</p>
                     <p>The third reaſon is the nature of humane frailty, conſidered as well in the Jeſuites, as in thoſe that oppoſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97877:43"/>and calumny them. On the the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites part, it is humane frailty that now and then ſome of them fall into errors and perhaps ſcandals too. This is the condition of man, that none can live quite blameleſſe, and in a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of never ſo perfect men, ſome will be imperfect. In ſo many hundred maſters as dayly teach ſchools in the Society, ſome will ſwerve from their rule, and either through indiſcretion, or paſſion commit faults which may juſtly be cenſured. The like is of the other imployments of preaching, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing, miſſions, and the reſt which I have numbred in the precedent chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, all which being hard imployments, and requiring a ſolid renunciation of ones ſelf, for to be conſtantly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed well, it muſt be expected that ſome will falter, and having ſet their hand to the plough look back.</p>
                     <p>Now whereas when any of theſe things happen, all prudent men, ought to compaſſionate humane infirmity, and by good counſel and advice endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to take away the fault, or at leaſt the Scandal; for the moſt part it happeneth quite contrary, through
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97877:43"/>the frailty (to call it no otherwiſe) of thoſe that oppoſe the Society. If one Jeſuit among a hundred have er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, preſently they magnify the fault, and multiply it too, and clap it on all Jeſuites, as a property of their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. For example if they ſee a Jeſuit exceed in cholar, preſently theſe Calumniatours comment on that fault, and firſt conclude that that man is haughty and proud, then that all Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites are arrogant and inſufferable men: and ſo they ſet the calumny a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, which runs through the whole nation, ſtill growing by the way, till at length the multitude takes the noiſe for an argument, and reſts fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, every one being well conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to believe ill of others. This is what <hi>I</hi> have very often obſerved to have happened to the Jeſuites: a little fault of one mans frailty, para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſed by malevolent gloſſers, hath often made a great noiſe, and when the matter hath been ſifted, the ſource of all has been at moſt a <hi>peccadilio,</hi> an overſight, a chance. Now if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that ſome Jeſuit committ a great fault againſt the precepts of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97877:44"/>God or leave his vocation, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that is rung out in a full peal, and all the Jeſuites in the World, muſt be laſhed by every mans tongue, for the fault which one committed, though all the reſt were againſt the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and more ſenſible of his fault then they would be of any humane loſſe, or even of death it ſelf. God be thanked ſuch ſcandals happen but very ſeldome; and perhaps that's one reaſon why the faults of the Jeſuites make ſo much noiſe, becauſe they happen ſeldom. Howſoever the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits have reaſon to relent this unjuſt proceeding of their adverſaries, which is both unchriſtian and unrational: Unchriſtian becauſe it is againſt all the rules of charity: unrational be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe very illogically theſe men draw a general concluſion out of particular premiſes. All lewd Women muſt not be concluded Saints, becauſe St. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalen</hi> was ſo, nor all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Traytours, becauſe <hi>Judas</hi> was ſo. The Jeſuits for the moſt part are vertuous and able men, if ſome times they err, they deſire a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble interpreter, not a ſower Critick.</p>
                     <q>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:97877:44"/>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eniam petimuſque damuſque viciſſim.</q>
                     <p>The fourth reaſon is the condition of the Jeſuits life which on the one ſide is publick in the view of all the World; and on the other ſide hath not that exteriour rigour, which may beſpeak veneration by a kind of looks of Vertue, or countenance of morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, which takes the multitude that is not able to ſee into the inſide of Vertues. Other religious orders are immured up in Cloiſters, where if they commit any fault, it is covered in ſilence and ſolitude. A rough ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid habit gets reverence to ſome: perpetual faſts give fame to others: others are credited by great auſterity. Others by daily begging of almes make their poverty and contempt of the World known and eſteemed. All do laudably; nor do I cite their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to tax them, but to commend them, whom the Society looketh at as their elder brothers. All that I ſay is, that the Society hath none of thoſe things which may ſerve for a ſconce to others if they fall. A Jeſuit
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97877:45"/>that is a Maſter, or Preacher, or Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionant, cannot err, but that he muſt have as many Witneſſes of his errour as there are men that he dealeth with. The life and habit of a Jeſuit, hath nothing that ſpeaks Rigour: 'tis a common life, ſuch as may beſeem poor Clergy Men that are tyed to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual labour: as it hath nothing of ſuperfluity, ſo it wanteth nothing that is neceſſary. This the Vulgar un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, but eaſily interpret a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs. I believe if I ſhould deſcribe the rigid life of the Charter-houſe Moncks in perpetuall ſilence, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſolitude, perpetual faſt and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, there would be found many hair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brain'd men who would preſently cry, <hi>The Devil is in theſe men.</hi> And the ſame Men if they ſhould be told all the Jeſuits life, would preſently cry, that <hi>They had an eaſie life, a merry life, alwayes fall of Good cheer.</hi> Theſe men may have the comfort that they are not the firſt Fools of the World: there were as very fools as they a long time ago. Chriſt our Saviour tells us ſo. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.18. <hi>Venit Joannes neque manducans neque bibens &amp; dicunt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97877:45"/>habet; venit Filius hominis man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducans &amp; bibens, &amp; dicunt ecce homo vorax &amp; potator vini. John came neither eating nor drinking,</hi> that is, with extream Rigour of faſt, and <hi>they ſay of him he hath the Devil in him.</hi> On the other ſide. <hi>The Son of Man comes eating and drinking,</hi> that is leading a common life, not refuſing a neceſſary diet, <hi>and they ſay he is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer and a Wine-bibber.</hi> So doth the multitude uſually miſinterpret ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and like ill Schollars alwayes conſtrue wrong. Nor is it only the multitude, ſome (for that muſt be ſaid too) ſome I ſay, even among Prieſts and Religious men reprehend the life of the Society. They are ſtartled to ſee the common life of the Jeſuits, and like St. <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciples they ask. <hi>Math.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Quare nos &amp; Phariſaei je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junamus frequenter, diſcipuli autem tui non jejundnt. Why do we and the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees faſt often, but your Diſciples fast not?</hi> They have ſet themſelves a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of life and a way of Rigour, which is laudable, but that which is not laudable, is, that when they ſee the Society go another way to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97877:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>on different from theirs, they imagine they are out of the way. And which is yet leſs laudable they fall ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into open complaints, when they ſee that the Jeſuits, (though there appear no extraordinary Rigour in their life to commend them to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the World) are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in a high opinion for Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Learning, and carry away the ball for conduct of Souls in moſt countries of Chriſtendome. This doth eaſily gall thoſe who are not ſolidly Vertuous: it makes them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, to ſee that eſteem, which they judge due to themſelves, paid to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in whom they acknowledge ſo little merit.</p>
                     <p>Yet this muſt be borne pationtly by the Jeſuits: nor muſt they change their inſtitute becauſe of wicked eyes that look on: they muſt not overload their Subjects who are wearied with their daily employments, for the judgement of other men. <hi>Wiſe Men ſee,</hi> (notwithſtanding the murmure of ſome) that there are very few Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the church of God more ſtrict, and bound to greater hardſhip then
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97877:46"/>the ſociety. Nor doth it import much, whether the mortification be in the brain, or on the back: the former is leaſt ſeen, but moſt felt. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will look on the employments of the Society will eaſily find, that they import as much pain and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, as any rule can eaſily do. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the rule of the Society obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, that every one ſhall uſe ſuch mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications, as, his employment and health conſidered, his Superiour or Ghoſtly Father ſhall think fit to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him. In conſequence to which rule I conceive the voluntary morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications uſed in the Society may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with moſt, and tranſcend many of the exacteſt obſervance. But they do not appear, and ſo thoſe who mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all by the outſide, eaſily judge wrong.</p>
                     <p>Theſe are then, as far as <hi>I</hi> can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the fountains and ſources of the animoſity that divers have againſt the ſociety. Now let us proceed to ſee what it is that is objected againſt the Society, and what is their anſwer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:97877:47"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CAP. V.</hi> The Objections made against the ſociety of Jeſus, which concern their life and Institute.</head>
                     <p>TWO things I deſire to advertiſe the Reader of, before <hi>I</hi> enter on the particular Objections. The one is that <hi>I</hi> ſhall deal ſincerely and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſetting down the objections and anſwers (as far as I know them) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſſembling, or publiſhing any thing; my intent being wholly bent on this to declare the truth, of which every one may judge as they ſee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The ſecond thing is, that when in the anſwer to theſe objections, <hi>I</hi> do clear (as I conceive <hi>I</hi> ſhall) the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, my meaning is not to ſay that never any man of the Society erred in thoſe points, no, that is not my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor would it be true: I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed in the former chapter that one of the cauſes which gives riſe to the calumnies made againſt the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97877:47"/>is the frailty of particular Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its, from which I never intend to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt them. But to ſhew that the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety is blameleſſe, is to ſhew that their Rule and Inſtitute, which in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is vigorouſly looked into, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids thoſe faults, and fenceth them out, and prevents them, and puniſheth them ſeverely when they are found, which is all that humane frailty can do. All this every judicious man will allow: and ſo I come to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and firſt to thoſe which are the moſt vulgar.</p>
                     <p>The firſt objection then, which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble talk layes to the Jeſuites is, that they are crafty. <hi>I</hi> anſwer that if by craft it be meant that the Jeſuits are not fools, not imprudent men, not headlong zealots, I hope it is all very true. The Jeſuits have a very pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Government, like to Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal mixt with Ariſtocracy. All de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on one, but one that hath his lawes fixed, and is bound to hear counſel in every occurrent of moment, and may be called to account. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Jeſuits do not eaſily admit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny amongſt them but ſuch as they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97877:48"/>hope may in time prove vertuous and able men. Further they ſet the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt eſteem, after vertue, on learning. And to ſecure the actions of all, every office and employment amongſt them hath ſet rules, made with long deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration and experience. Finally no Jeſuit is allowed to follow his own <hi>dictamen,</hi> but all are regulated by the advice of Superiours, Maſters, and Ghoſtly Fathers. All this gives the Jeſuites much advantage and dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in action, and will effect, that (with Gods bleſſing) their endeavours will ſucceed, which is that which prudence aimeth at. But if by <hi>craft</hi> is meant as the word ſounds (ſpecially in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection) a practiſe of compaſſing their ends by wiles and tricks, or an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to overreach others by undue means, it is very falſe and very farr from the Jeſuits. This may appear firſt by looking on the end of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety deſcribed in the firſt chapter. Did ever any man go about to cheat ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for his good that was cheated? Yet the end of the Society is the good of their neighbour. Next the means the Society uſeth to compaſſe this end,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97877:48"/>are teaching, preaching, catechiſing, and the reſt numbred in the third chapter; All which are no actions of cheating or cozenage: and beſides, they are done by the Jeſuites frankly and freely, without hoping or admitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſalary or reward. Do men, think you, uſe to take great pains in trickes and double dealing for no advantage of their own? Laſtly all the Kings and Princes and their Councels, all the Cities and Nations that hold the ſociety in eſteem, confute this objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For they all judge the Jeſuits prudent men. Men of ſolid Vertue and Learning: and on that account they truſt the Jeſuits with their dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pleadges, their children, and their conſciences. Now if this Objection were true, all thoſe muſt be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be of very weak judgment, that have been ſo long gulled, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that for prudence, which is but craft, for vertue which is vice, for honeſty which is a cheat. But the ignorant, ſeeing that God uſually bleſſeth the endeavours of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, taketh that for craft, which is done by the rules of true prudence.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:97877:49"/>The ſecond objection is, that the Jeſuits are rich. This is another of thoſe Objections which in the tongues and ears of inconſiderate people makes a great noiſe to cry down the Jeſuits. <hi>I</hi> anſwer. Suppoſe this were true, and that the Jeſuits were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed rich and very rich; yet 'tis no crime to be rich, but to uſe riches ill is the fault. Biſhops are Rich, Canons are rich, Monaſteries of Moncks are rich, and no body com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains: nay all good men are glad to ſee wealth in their hands who will uſe it well for the honour of God: it was for this reaſon that the piety of our Anceſtours was ſo bountifull to Churches and Monaſteries, becauſe they thought their riches beſt placed where they might be beſt uſed for the glory of God. And what then if the Jeſuites were rich? Yet 'tis not ſo: They are actually poor, and very poor: they are not ſo well furniſhed as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the pooreſt of all the Clengy. The whole annual rent of a Colledge, which keepeth about twenty Jeſuits to teach and preach, is not uſually ſo great, as what oftentimes one Canon
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97877:49"/>poſſeſſeth. All the Colledges in a Province (<hi>Flanders</hi> for example) are not worth the Revenues of one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery. I can aſſure you this, that there are but few Colledges ſo well rented in all <hi>Europe,</hi> as to have year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly twenty pound a Man for every Religious perſon that they maintain. Yet out of this twenty pound a Man, is to be defalked the expenſes of the Church, the expenſes of the Fabrike, the expenſes of Strangers; either of the ſociety, who come that way, or of ſecular Men, who upon occaſions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire themſelves to the Colledges for to make the ſpiritual exerciſe. All which expenſes deducted, the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is not ſo great, but that in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Fathers need daily almes for to buy their bread, almoſt in all the Colledges of <hi>Europe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But that which Malevolent men lay hold of to make ignorant people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Jeſuites are rich is, that they ſee the Jeſuites Churches ſplendid, and richly furniſht, and their ſchools and halls for publick exerciſes mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificently built. This they take for riches, and they do not conſider, that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97877:50"/>theſe works argue the devotion and magnificence of the Founders, not the riches of the Jeſuites. Churches are great for the concurſe of many that there ſerve God; and ſchools are large to receive many Schollars. 'Tis the good of the Town that good ſchools be built: it maketh not the Maſter one penny the richer; nor is it any comfort to him to paſs out of a large ſchool, through a fair Hall built for publick exerciſes of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to a poor garret, there to ſpend the reſt of his time in Solitude, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Prayer, and Study. An ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritious man cannot center here, though a religious Spirit finds more ſolace in the bare walls of a narrow cell, then in the ſpecious magnificence of ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buildings.</p>
                     <p>Another reaſon why the Jeſuites are commonly thought rich is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe generally every one of them is ſufficiently provided of neceſſaries. Yet this proceedeth not from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riches then the Treaſure of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. It is the rule and practiſe of the Society, that amongſt them every one muſt be equally provided of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97877:50"/>what is their's is common to all. They have no Abbots who have their <hi>quota,</hi> a part for to keep State and publick Hoſpitality, as ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religious very laudably do. Their Rectours eat and drink no better then their Porters and Cooks do; all out of the ſame pot, and at the ſame Table. This equal diviſion makes that their Almes and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues being equally ſhared amongſt all, none abound, nor none want, or if they do? 'tis when all want. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not me in this, believe thoſe that have lived (as many Gentlemen in <hi>England</hi> have done) in the ſemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and convicts of the Society, they can tell you that all Jeſuites fare and lodge alike, all are clad alike, all equally attended in health and ſickneſſe. There is no difference, ſave only the reſpect due to age and ſuperiority.</p>
                     <p>The third objection is, that the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites are ambitious: but what are they ambitious of? If a hard miſſion be to be undergone, if Priſons and Hoſpitals be to be viſited, if any be to be expoſed to contagions, or peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, then (thanks be to God) the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97877:51"/>ſuperiours find them all ambitious of ſuch employments. But for Titles and Honours, they are ſo far from aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to them, that I think no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity in the World can better plead <hi>Not guilty</hi> then they. All that are profeſſed in the Society make this vow. <hi>Promitto nunquamme acturum vel prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſurum ne indirectè quidem, ut in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquam praelationem, vel dignitatem eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar vel promovear. I promiſe that I will never procure or pretend (not ſo much as indirectly) to be choſen into any dignity or prelacy.</hi> This vow they make to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all ambition of dignities or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments within the ſociety. Now for other Titles out of the Society, as of Biſhop or Cardinal and the like, they Vow thus: <hi>Promitto praeterea nunquam me curaturum praetenſutumve extraſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem praelationem aliquam vel dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, nec conſenſurum in mei electionem quantum in me fuerit, niſi coactum obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiâ ejus qui mibi praecipere potest ſub paenâ peccati. I promiſe beſides that I will never procure or pretend unto any dignity or Prelacy out of the Society, and that as much as lyeth in me, I will not conſent to my Election, unleſs I
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97877:51"/>be forced by obedience of him who can command me under pain of ſin.</hi> If they who make this vow, and keep it moſt exactly (as the ſociety hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver done) muſt be called ambitious, what ſhall we ſay of thoſe that deſire and procure Dignities and Prelacies. I would fain ſee thoſe that tax the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of ambition, lay their hands on their breaſt, and make the ſame vows which the Jeſuites do. If they refuſe that, and yet would not be judged ambitious, though they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend (as they ſay) to prefer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Legal wayes, let them change their ſentence, and give a milder cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſociety. Certainly the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites have had many able men, who have been Confeſſours and Preachers to Kings, Princes, and Popes; and by that means they have had a fair door open to honour. Nay many times honours have been thruſt upon them; but their reſolution, and only their reſolution to avoid all honours, hath kept them off. Some few of the Society have been raiſed to Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call dignities, but it is known that thay accepted not thoſe dignities but by
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97877:52"/>force, and ſo kept the rigour of their vow. All this makes it clear that this Objection is wholly ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
                     <p>The fourth objection; that the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites are nice and lead a lazie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate life. This objection is anſwered in the end of the precedent chapter, and it needeth no further refutal, then the bare rehearſal of the employments wherein the Jeſuites are buſied. How can any man judge them lazie who embrace ſo many employments of ſuch fatigue, for the publick good? How can they be judged nice, who ſpend a great part of their life in ſchools, and never refuſe to go to Hoſpitals and Priſons, and treat with beggars for the good of their ſouls? But the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites have a decent habit, and by their rule have a great care of cleanli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in their houſe, in their cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and Refectory, and above all in their Church; this they who will nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name all vertue call nicety: as the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they keep in their Schools, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void confuſion, and eaſe their labour, they call Lazineſs; and with their good leave <hi>I</hi> call their whole objection ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="89" facs="tcp:97877:52"/>The fiſt Objection; Jeſuites are dangerous men, becauſe they meddle in intrigues of State, and thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Court affairs. I anſwer that if ever any Jeſuit doth do ſo, he tranſgreſſeth his rule, and committeth a grievous ſin againſt an expreſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of obedience; which is ſet down in theſe very words in their Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, under the Title <hi>Cenſurae &amp; Praecepta. In virtute ſanctae obedientiae praecipitur noſtris omnibus, ne quis pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis &amp; ſaecularibus Principum negotiis, ulla ratione ſe immiſceat, nec quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumvis per quoſcunque requiſitus aut ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus, ejuſmodi politicas res tractandas ſuſcipiat.</hi> 
                        <q>All ours are commanded in Vertue of Holy obedience, that none do any wiſe intermeddle in publick and ſecular buſineſſes of Princes, nor upon any intreaty or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry do embrace ſuch State affairs.</q> Can there be more caution uſed then to forbid this under the higheſt penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that can be, that is under mortal ſin? for 'tis a mortal ſin to tranſgreſs a precept. Truly when I have ſome times reflected on this precept, <hi>I</hi> have been ſo far from ſiding with the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:97877:53"/>that I have thought Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns might juſtly except againſt this rigour. For it ſeems to me that by this precept Princes are excluded from making that uſe of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which otherwiſe they juſtly might. It may happen that a Jeſuit may be as fit to be entruſted with publick affairs of State, as other Church men are, whom we ſee often employed. Why may it not be as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a King, if he ſo pleaſe, to uſe a Jeſuite, as a Fryar, a Monck, a Canon, a Biſhop, (who is wedded to his Church) or a Cardinal? We have ſeen of all theſe men that have very fortunately managed State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. <hi>I</hi> ſee no other, ſolution, but that it is for the publick good, that whilſt ſome Churchmen laudably ſerve their Princes in this kind, others ſhould (as the Jeſuits do) avoid all actions of pomp and States matters. But happily this objection proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from thoſe that cannot diſtinguiſh betwixt Temporal and Spirituall. They ſee that in moſt Courts there are ſome Jeſuites neer the perſons of the Princes and Soveraigns, and chief
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97877:53"/>Courtiers: I mean thoſe who are their Confeſſours or Preachers. This makes many cry out of the Jeſuites as med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlers in State affairs. They might as well ſay, that the Phyſitians are States men, becauſe there is no Prince that hath not his Phyſitian as well as his Confeſſor or Preacher. But the Phyſitian, you will ſay, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his buſineſs; and I anſwer that the Jeſuite alſo attendeth to his. And if either of them hear any thing of State matters, 'tis but what the Princes pleaſe to communicate, which is no crime, nor doth it make either of them States men.</p>
                     <p>The ſixth objection. The Jeſuites cannot be truſted, becauſe they reveal all ſecrets, even confeſſions, to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours. I anſwer firſt, that this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, if it were true, would prove the former objection to be null; for if they reveal all, they are not fit to be States-men, whoſe firſt maxime ought to be ſecreſie. But it is falſe, as all thoſe know who uſually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt the Jeſuits with their conſcience. <hi>England</hi> ſaw <hi>F. Garnet</hi> rather choſe to dye then to reveal a ſecret of confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97877:54"/>And beſides this in all matters that require a natural ſecret, the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits know their obligation as well as others. Nor doth their rule, or can their ſuperiour oblige them to reveal any thing in this kind. True it is, that the Jeſuits among themſelves, for the publick good, give one another leave to reveal to the Superiour the faults which they ſee in them. This is by publick conſent among themſelves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the good of all, and it reacheth not out of their own community, nor toucheth externes. And beſides no Jeſuit can undertake an imployment, or go a journey without acquainting his ſuperiour, and having his leave. All this is for Domeſtick Order. But whereſoever any one openeth a ſecret to any Jeſuit for counſel, or the good of his conſcience, there the Jeſuits obſerve the ſame rules of ſecrecy which other honeſt and religious men are bound unto.</p>
                     <p>But becauſe in this objection I have mentioned <hi>F. Garnet,</hi> I muſt ſay a word or two concerning him. The cauſe of his death, was that having in confeſſion heard of the wicked deſign
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97877:54"/>of ſome of thoſe who were contrivers of the Gun-powder treaſon, he did not reveal it. Upon this he was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of treaſon. And truly <hi>I</hi> do not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Proteſtants, who know not the Sacramet and ſeal of Confeſſion, ſhould cry out of him for it: but <hi>I</hi> wonder that ſome Catholicks and Prieſts ſhould lay that treaſon on the Jeſuites doctrine. And for a full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction <hi>I</hi> deſire the judicious Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to conſider three things. Firſt of all. Father <hi>Garnet</hi> did nothing in that concealment, which every Prieſt in <hi>England</hi> and in all the World, will not ſay was the Duty of a Catholick Prieſt. Every Catholick knoweth, that a Prieſt cannot reveal any ſecret imparted to him in confeſſion for any Good in the World. Chriſt hath commanded that ſecret ſhould not be broke for any good imaginable. So Father <hi>Garnet</hi> did nothing but what all Prieſts will profeſſe to be their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. It was his chance to be in the caſe, but if any body elſe had been there, he would have done the ſame. I intend not to diſpute why this ſecret is ſuch, or whence it is proved, but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97877:55"/>only <hi>I</hi> ſay that all Catholicks believe it to be ſuch, and all Prieſts profeſs that they do and will ever keep the ſecret of confeſſion in all things whatſoever. So that this cannot be laid to the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits as their doctrine.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, I deſire the Proteſtant to reflect, that this ſecrecy though it be allowed, can bring no prejudice to any Soveraign or State, but may probably bring ſome good. For if this ſecrecy be not allowed, no body will ever reveal ſuch wicked deſignes to any Ghoſtly Father. Whereas if upon confidence of ſecrecy, they do reveal it, the Ghoſtly Father may likely diſwade them, by ſhewing them the enormity of the fact. Good counſel is a great preſervative from ſin: and nothing precipitates a man more headlong into deſperate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts then want of counſel. When a man conſults only with his own paſſion and ruminates by himſelf his melancholy deſignes, the miſchief takes ſtill deeper root, which had it been vented would often have been diſſipated. That wicked man who murdered King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97877:55"/>
                        <hi>France,</hi> being asked why he did not reveal his temptation to ſome good Ghoſtly Father, anſwered, that he thought that if he had done ſo, the Ghoſtly Father muſt have revealed it. This error of his, as he profeſſed at his examination made him ſmother this ſin in confeſſion. So he went on in his deſign, which very likely he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver done, if he had ſpoken plain, and revealed his temptation in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It is true <hi>F. Garnet</hi> did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſſwade thoſe perfidious trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and could not effect it. Yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have often hindred ſinners from their wicked deſignes, by good counſel given in confeſſion.</p>
                     <p>The third thing which I deſire the Proteſtant to conſider is, that God, to clear <hi>F. Garnet</hi> from any treaſon, and ſhew that he accepted his death as a Martyrdome, did honour him, with the wonderful imprinting of his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture on ſome of the ſtrawes on which his blood fell. This is writ by divers; the ſtrawes with the Picture in them were ſeen by many, and by K. <hi>James</hi> himſelf. And among others, <hi>I</hi> know a perſon of note, who was preſent, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97877:56"/>had formerly known <hi>F. Garnet</hi> and ſaw the ſtraws: He was a Proteſtant, and one who did not eaſily believe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miracles, but (as many do) laught at them. Yet when <hi>I</hi> asked him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he thought, that this could be natural? He anſwered that without dout it was ſupernatural, and that it was impoſſible ſo plain a picture ſhould be made by any art in ſo little a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. All this I have ſaid not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the controverſy concerning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, or the fact of <hi>F. Garnet,</hi> but only to evince, that the Jeſuits have no doctrine in this point, but what all Catholick Prieſts profeſſe, and which, as <hi>I</hi> conceive, can prejudice no body. And certainly thoſe Proteſtants, who did ſometime in <hi>England</hi> practiſe confeſſion, thought thoſe that heard confeſſions amongſt them to be obliged to keep ſecret all the ſins, and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which any ſhould reveal unto them in confeſſion.</p>
                     <p>The ſeventh objection, the Jeſuites make a vow to the Pope, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be ſuppoſed not to be ſo loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al as others, being already tyed to a forreign prince, and therefore but
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97877:56"/>half Subjects. I anſwer that that vow is only in order to the propogation of the Ghoſpel which can prejudice no body. So ſay the Conſtitutions of the Society, part. 5. c. 3. <hi>Tota inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio quarti hujus voti fuit &amp; eſt circa Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones, &amp; ſic intelligi oportet literas A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicas ubi de hac obedientia loquuntur All the intention of this fourth vow, was and is concerning Miſſions, and ſo the Apostolical letters are to be understoood where they ſpeak of this obedience.</hi> What the Miſſions are I explicated in the third Chapter. And ſurely no prince hath ever been prejudiced by this vow. Nor is it ſpecially to be object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Jeſuits that they have an obligation of obedience to the Pope; All Catholick Biſhops take an oath to the Pope, nor doth any King or Prince ſuffer by that oath. And St. <hi>Francis</hi> the Seraphical Father promiſed for himſelf and all his Fryars Obedience to Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the third and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, as <hi>Cordova</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſuper. reg. c.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>circa finem.</hi> And Saint <hi>Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture in Expoſitione reg. c.</hi> 1. calleth that promiſe a ſpecial vow, in theſe words, <hi>Etſi totus clerus &amp; religioſorum
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97877:57"/>univerſitas teneatur firmitèr Apostolico domino obedire, tamen huic debito vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum adjecit ſpeciale. Although all the Clergy and all religious orders be bound to obey the Pope, yet St.</hi> Francis <hi>would add a ſpecial vow to this Obligation.</hi> For my part <hi>I</hi> think that no man, who rightly conſidereth what the Vow im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth can be ſtartled at it: nor can a vow to go to the <hi>Indies</hi> for good of ſouls, if I be ſent, more offend my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, then a Vow of going on Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or any other Vow. This ſheweth how vain a thing it is to object to the Jeſuits their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of the Pope: whereas on the other ſide they depend of the Pope leſs then any of the clergy or religious men; ſpeaking of that dependance, which may byaſs their affection or make them ſide with the Pope, ſince they cannot admit of thoſe Eccleſiaſtical dignities, by which the Pope may oblige thoſe who can accept them, and as we ſee dayly do purſue them. What the Jeſuits obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is in refuſing dignities, I have ſaid in the third objection in this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and I think no man can ſay that they ever infringed that vow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:97877:57"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CAP. VI.</hi> Objections made against the Jeſuites Doctrine.</head>
                     <p>AS the Jeſuites Lives and form of Inſtitute have found many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, ſo their Doctrine hath heen oppoſed by many. Some as well Proteſtants as Catholicks have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned them by oppoſing reaſon to reaſon. Theſe the Jeſuites account their friends, and thank them for their pains. For to canvaſs doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full matters, by ſifting one another's ſentence, helps to whet the wits on both ſides. There is a friendly claſhing in Schools, and a ſtriking fire in diſpute, which ſerves only to give light to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure queſtions. This oppoſition the Jeſuites uſe not only with others, but even among themſelves, nor do they fear any breach of charity in this amicable enmity, which is for the profit of both parties.</p>
                     <p>Another ſort of adverſaries oppoſe their Doctrine not by reaſoning, but by railing, by clamours, by forging
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97877:58"/>and falſying their books; as doth the authour of the Provincial letters, who never had any care of ſpeaking truth: and ſo his work hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten condemned, and burnt by the hangman, as containing nothing but ſlanders. Indeed ſuch adverſaries de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſuch entertainment: for this is not to impugne Authors, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly them. Theſe, to ſay truth, deſerve no anſwer; they ſhould be whipt out of Schools, if they had their deſert. Yet to ſatisfie others ſometimes they muſt be anſwered who merit not ſo much as to be heard.</p>
                     <p>From theſe adverſaries not of learning but of truth proceed the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt the Jeſuites Doctrine which I intend to take notice of in this chapter. And their Firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is that the Jeſuites teach the Doctrine of Equivocation and mental reſervation, and therefore they can not be truſted. I anſwer that the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits reach nothing in this matter which is not the common Doctrine of all Schools, and Univerſities none excepted. Nor do I ſee how it can be denyed unleſs we will ſay that it is
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97877:58"/>lawfull to lye, as <hi>Statera morum</hi> doth for then we may infer as that book doth, pag. 172 that it is clear they are in an errour who ſcorning the name of a ly, make uſe of Equivocation. But that Author will not find any of his opinion, nor doth he leſſen but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the difficulty. The ſumme there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the Doctrine concerning Equivocation is this: That it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ill done to lye, but not alwayes ill to conceal the truth by ambiguous ſpeech, that is by Equivocation or mental reſervation. When there is a juſt cauſe to conceal the truth, then it is lawfull (ſay the Divines) to uſe ambiguous ſpeech; on the contrary when there is not a juſt cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the truth then it is a ſin to equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate. Now when the cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the truth is juſt, or not, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on the particular circumſtance of every occurrence, for which there is no rule can be ſet. This is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Equivocation wherein the Society hath nothing particular, but teacheth that and only that in which both Catholick and Proteſtant Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours agree. Among the Catholick
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97877:59"/>Doctours that teach this are St <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin,</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and after him a torrent of School Divines. Among the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants are divers mentioned in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants Apology: as <hi>Peter Martyr, Zuinglius, Willet, Melancton, Luther, Muſculus, Wiclef,</hi> and divers others cited at length in the 7 ſection of the 3 Tract. under the Let. M. number 76. and in the 703. page of the Impreſſion An. Dom. 1608. Though of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors there cited, ſome will not uſe the name of Equivocation or mental reſervation, but call theſe doubtfull ſpeeches <hi>officious lyes;</hi> which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they ſay one is bound ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to uſe. So <hi>Luther</hi> there cited, ſaith of <hi>Rahab,</hi> and concludeth that there is an officious lye, by which men provide for the fame and ſafety of their Neighbour. <hi>Igitur honeſtum ac pium mendacium eſt, ac potius officum charitatis appellandum.</hi> And <hi>Oſiander</hi> there cited, ſaith of the Calviniſts thus, <hi>Hanc maximam ſou regulam habent Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinistae licere pro gloria Chriſti mentiri. The Calminiſts have this for a ground or Principle, that it is lawfull to lye for
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97877:59"/>the glory of Chriſt.</hi> Yet Catholicks generally do not allow of lying, but (as many Proteſtants) of concealing the truth by Equivocation.</p>
                     <p>Now that this Doctrine may, and muſt be ſometimes allowed, examples will make manifeſt. I will inſtance in one. When his Majeſty after <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> fight was conſtrained to ſhelter himſelf in <hi>Boſcobell,</hi> there was, as we all know, narrow ſearch made after him. Among the reſt one of the <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drils,</hi> (thoſe loyal Subjects, ever to be commended in all hiſtory) was asked where the King was. He anſwered that he knew not: meaning that he knew not for to tell them. He thought he might and ought in that caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the truth. And all the Jeſuites in the World are of his opinion. He was bound there under pain of high Treaſon to Equivocate. And thoſe that deny Equivocation to be lawfull, let them ſay what they would have done? Sure I am, that if they would not in that caſe have uſed Equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or montal Reſervation, they muſt have been either Lyars or Traytours. The doctrine therefore of Equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97877:60"/>teacheth only this, that when there is a juſt neceſſity of concealing the truth, then you may equivocate: but when there is not a juſt reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the truth, then it is a ſin to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocate, becauſe ſuch equivocation containeth fraud and double dealing contrary to Chriſtian Charity, and that candour and ſincerity which is neceſſary for commerce among men. And in this the Jeſuits are no wayes ſingular, they teach but what all teach.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond Objection is that the Jeſuits teach that horrid maxime. <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des non eſt ſervanda haereticis. Faith is not to be kept to Hereticks.</hi> I anſwer that, that maxime is point blanck a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the doctrine of the Jeſuits. <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> was a Jeſuit: hear what he ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Tract. c.</hi> 12. <hi>de Charitate. Tam. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitae quam alii doctores Catholici aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te profitentur ac docent: fidom publicam haereticis datam inviolabiliter &amp; ſine ullo diſpenſationis aut abſolutionis reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio ſervandam eſſe. As well Jeſuits as all other Catholick Doctours openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and teach that publick faith given to Hereticks is inviolably to be kept
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97877:60"/>without any remedy of diſpenſatirn or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. Coutzen</hi> was alſo a Jeſuit: and he in his book called <hi>Deſceptatio de ſecretis Societatis Jeſu,</hi> maketh this profeſſion in his own name, and in the name of all the Jeſuits pag. 86. <hi>Nos docemus Haeretico, Judaeo, Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, Turcae, Rebelli ſubdito, fidem datam ſervandam eſſe, nec modo non aperte vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olandam ſed nec ambiguâ fraude, nec aequivocatione eludendam. We teach that faith is to be kept, to Hereticks, to Jewes, to Gentiles, to Turks, to Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Subjects: and this faith is not only not be openly broken, but alſo not be elu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with fraud or equivocation but ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be kept.</hi> This I hope will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy that that maxime is not the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites.</p>
                     <p>The third and main Objection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Jeſuites Doctrine is, that they maintain the Popes authority in prejudice to Soveraignity, teaching that the Pope hath power to depoſe Kings. This is the Objection with which the Jeſuites are every where cryed down. And becauſe it is ſo much made of by the adverſaries of the ſociety, I ſhall humbly intreat the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97877:61"/>Reader to give me leave to be a little more large in my anſwer. I ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as to matter of fact, for I mean not to meddle with the queſtion other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that the Jeſuits never did at any time teach in this matter otherwiſe then what was the common doctrine of other Doctours in the Catholick Church, and for the preſent they are leſſe chargeable with this Doctrine then any others. The firſt part of this aſſertion, I prove by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Henry</hi> the great, our dear Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns Grandfather, who (when this doctrine of the Popes depoſing Kings was objected againſt the Jeſuites, as an argument why they ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue baniſhed out of <hi>France</hi>) ſaid to the Parliament theſe words, <hi>I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that in averring and defending the Popes Authority they differ not from other Catholick Divines.</hi> This the <hi>French</hi> Stories averre, this the ſpeech of that great King makes appear (as you may ſee in the ſpeech it ſelf which I have inſerted in the next chapter) this the actions of the ſame King (if his words were not exſtant) would make plain to all the world, for how can it be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97877:61"/>that he who was in the account of all, a very wiſe man, ſhould admit into his Kingdom men that held trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable doctrine? How ſhould he be poſſibly ſuppoſed ſo forgetful of his own good, and the ſafety of his own poſterity, as that he ſhould plead for men who were charged to hold do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine prejudicial to Monarchy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examining whether their accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were true? No, no, he was not ſo weak, as to become the Oratour, for his own ruine; He would never have made it his buſineſſe to plead for the Jeſuites and command their admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, nay further to take them into his familiar acquaintaince, make them his confeſſours and build them Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and bequeath his heart unto them, if he had not been fully ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that their doctrine conteined no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſingular to the prejudice of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty. I eaſily believe that thoſe who have already calumnied the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in this matter, will endeavour ſome ſleeveleſſe anſwer to this autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the words and actions of ſo great a King. But withall I confide that his Majeſty will give more credit
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97877:62"/>to the ſingle aſſertion of his Grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then to ten thouſand detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and all wiſe men will joyn in his Majeſties opinion.</p>
                     <p>But to go on and prove both firſt and ſecond part of what I aſſerted. Nothing elſe need be ſaid to make all my aſſertion evidently clear, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give a true hiſtorical account of what hath been done in this matter, which I will do ſincerely and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The opinion then of the Popes authority in depoſing of princes was held by many religious and clergy men before any of the Society writ of it. For example there were ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cited for this opinion of the renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed order of the <hi>Benedictines, Gregory</hi> the 7th. and other Abbots that joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him (as <hi>Deſiderius</hi> Abbot of <hi>Mont Caſſin,</hi> and <hi>Anſelmus Lucenſis</hi> did) and <hi>Panormitanus &amp;c.</hi> of the order of Saint <hi>Auſtiue, Aegidius Romanus, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtinus Triumphus, &amp;c.</hi> of St. <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks</hi> order, <hi>St. Thomas, St. Anthoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Cajetan, &amp;c.</hi> of the <hi>Franciſcans, St. Bonaventure, Johannes de Capiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, Pelagius Alvarius Alexander Ales, &amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Carmelites, Waldenſis</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con;</hi>
                        <pb n="109" facs="tcp:97877:62"/>of the Clergy very many Prieſts and Biſhops and Cardinals, as <hi>Gerſon</hi> Doctour of <hi>Paris,</hi> &amp;c. Of Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers <hi>Bartolus</hi> and <hi>Baldus</hi> &amp;c. Theſe and many more were cited in Shooles for this Doctrine, which <hi>Barclay</hi> rightly calleth the common doctrine of both Canoniſts and Divines, though notwithſtanding it is to be obſerved that none of theſe, nor no Catholick Divine ever gave the pope an Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power to depoſe at his liſt, as now ſome though very falſly preſume; Their opinions were modifyed ſo that their books ſtood in eſteem and were not thought to have deſerved ſo ill at princes hands as now ſome would make them ſeem. All which I do not ſry to defend their opinions as good, but only as declaring matter of fact I ſay theſe and many more were cited in Schools for this doctrine; as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion before the Society was in the World: as beſides what I have ſaid is maneſtly proved in the Oration which Cardinal <hi>Peron</hi> made to the 3. Eſtate in <hi>France.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whileſt then this was the opinion of Schools, <hi>Beliarmine</hi> writ his contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97877:63"/>and in the matter <hi>de ſummo pontifice</hi> he taught this doctrine, and he took his arguments as he profeſſeth himſelf in great part out of <hi>Sanders,</hi> a ſecular prieſt. After <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> partly to vindicate him, partly on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other accounts four or five Jeſuites more writ of the ſame matter, alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing authours, who had writ before them, and taking for the moſt part their reaſon out of former writers that ſtood in Libraries and were read with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controll in Schooles: And this is that which <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth ſaid, that <hi>he wasſure Jeſuites taught nothing in this matter which did differ from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Catholicks.</hi> But it was not enough for the ſociety to be as wary as others.</p>
                     <p>Their doctrine therefore, after the death of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth their great Protector, was highly contradicted, ſpecially in <hi>France,</hi> and much noiſe there was. The Jeſuits then ſeeing that this doctrine was <hi>Lapis offenſionis,</hi> and bred diſguſt becauſe they taught it, to take away all complaint of the ſociety, reſolved never to ſay more of that matter: ſo F. <hi>Claudius Aquavaria</hi> the fifth General of the Society made
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97877:63"/>a prohibition concerning this matter on the 5th. of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1616. But becauſe that prohibition ſeemed not efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enough, to prevent all inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences and give the World full ſatisfaction, Father <hi>Mutius Vitelleſchi</hi> the ſixth General of the ſociety in the year 1626 on the thirteenth of <hi>August</hi> made a precept of obedience, by which all Jeſuites are obliged under pain of damnation, never to write, diſpute, teach or print, any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that matter. The precept is extant in an Epiſtle of Father <hi>Mutius,</hi> and from thence inſerted as a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual precept into the 8th. Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>in fine,</hi> it runneth thus, <hi>Ordinamus in virtute ſanctae obedientiae ne quis in poſterum materiam de potestate ſummi pontifieis ſuper principes, eos deponendi, &amp;c. tractet aut libris editis aut ſcriptis quibuſcùnque nec publice diſputet, aut doceat in ſeholis, ut occaſiones omnes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſionis &amp; querelarum praecidantur.</hi> This is the precept which hath now ſtood this 35 years, and never was infringed by any one; fince the year 26 nothing hath been ſaid of this queſtion in ſchools, or ſermons, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97877:64"/>diſcourſes nothing hath been printed of it in the ſociety. This care the ſociety hath had to avoid all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive queſtions. And truly I conceive it were much to be deſired that all other Divines as well Proteſtants as Catholicks were obliged in the ſame manner, to perpetuall ſilence in theſe matters.</p>
                     <p>But whilſt the ſociety hath uſed this caution, others have not done ſo. They taught it before the ſociety was in the World, and ſome continue it ſtill: All this makes me reflect on the proceeding of thoſe who love to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile the ſociety right or wrong, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if theſe mens zeal were for his Majeſties ſafety as they pretend, they would never have picked out the Jeſuits amongſt all others to blame for this doctrine: they would have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to have rooted it out where it is main tained, not where it is already ſilenced and baniſhed the ſchools. They might have found Doctrine more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their invectives which concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our times and our Nation neerer. For example the Author of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on the Oaths of Supremacy and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97877:64"/>Allegiance,</hi> telleth us, page the 67<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. that in <hi>Spain</hi> Schools are connived at ſtill in teaching this doctrine of the popes temporal power. If this be true why doth he not cite theſe ſchools? are they Monks? are they Fryars? are they Clergy men? for <hi>I</hi> am ſure they are not Jeſuits. But his reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to make the Jeſuits odious, will not give him leave to name any body elſe. Again whilſt theſe men would baniſh all the Jeſuites out of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe ſome Jeſuites did fourty or fifty years ago teach that doctrine, why do they not cry out of ſuch Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men as lately have writ the ſame doctrine and more too.</p>
                     <p>I will not cite them as not willing to propagate any of this kind of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, though it be but in a citation. But certainly they might have been taken notice of by any that did really intend rather to root out ſuch kind of Doctrine then to impugne the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites.</p>
                     <p>The fourth Objection againſt the Jeſuites Doctrine is that they teach the killing of Kings, though under the name of Tyrants. So <hi>Mariana a Spaniſh</hi>
                        <pb n="114" facs="tcp:97877:65"/>Jeſuit teacheth, and therefore ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> his books burnt at <hi>Paris.</hi> I anſwer, that <hi>Mariana</hi> did in the year 1599. print a book entituled, <hi>De Rege et Regis inſtitutione,</hi> which he dedicated to <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Spain.</hi> In this book he did teach a doctrine, (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Dominicus Soto l.</hi> 5. <hi>de jure &amp; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticia q.</hi> 1. <hi>a.</hi> 3.) contrary to the judgment of the ſociety, of killing, not Kings, but of Tyrants: which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine the ſociety condemned and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, and the other Doctours of the ſociety all unanimouſly impugned it. That you may know the truth, <hi>I</hi> muſt do as in the laſt Objection, that is, give you a narrative of the paſſage. When then the General of the ſociety, <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Aquaviva</hi> underſtood that <hi>Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> had put out an opinion of ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence, he writ to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the ſociety in <hi>France,</hi> who had acquainted him with the whole matter, in theſe words, as Father <hi>Coton</hi> ſets them down in a Letter to the Queen Regent of <hi>France. We have been very ſorry that no body percieved the fault, untill the books were printed; the which notwithstanding we have preſently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97877:65"/>to be corrected, and will uſe great care hereafter that ſuch things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen no more.</hi> This paſſed in the year 1606. four years before the <hi>Sorbon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>Mariana's</hi> book, which was <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1610. <hi>July.</hi> 4. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this the General of the ſociety did give order for the correcting that place, and ſuppreſſing the book till it were corrected; but ſome copies being abroad (before the error was known to the General) which the ſociety would gladly have called in, the heirs of one called <hi>Weebel</hi> a Proteſtant, or as ſome <hi>French</hi> Authors call him, a <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonot,</hi> printed it again at their own charges. And this for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as it may be preſumed, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lucre or malice to the ſociety: After this the General ſent a ſtrict command to all of the ſociety, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in <hi>Cong.</hi> 8. <hi>tit. Cenſurae,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pain of Excommunication, inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and divers other penalties, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting all of the ſociety from wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or teaching in private or publick, or adviſing that it is lawful to kill Kings or Princes, or machin their death upon any pretence of Tyranny.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97877:66"/>And all the Authours of the ſociety, excepting only <hi>Mariana,</hi> both before and ſince him, perpetually taught and teach the contrary; ſaying <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema</hi> to all thoſe that teach, or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe any ſuch doctrine, condemned long ſince by the Councel of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> This is what the ſociety hath done to ſtop that book, and root out the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which I conceive will clearly ſhew, that this Doctrine is not reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly laid to the ſociety; Nor can it be Objected but by them who will have it, that the fault of any one of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety muſt like Original ſin infect all for ever and unpardonably, to whom <hi>I</hi> can give no other anſwer, but that <hi>I</hi> wiſh them more wit, and leſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</p>
                     <p>But now, leſt what I have ſaid in theſe two laſt Objections may give the Reader occaſion of Scandal, I have two things to Admoniſh him of.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is, that I have ſaid nothing but what I conceived preciſely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to defend the innocency of the ſociety, wrongfully impugned, and ſlandered by divers libells, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97877:66"/>by the Author of the <hi>Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Oathes of Allegiance and Supremacy, in his</hi> 9. <hi>Sect. I</hi> would confute the particulars, but I conceive on the one ſide, that which I have here writ is enough to make any body able to confute them, and on the otherſide, the ſuppoſed Authour of that work, having before thoſe of his own Order, that could and did call him to account, renounced the work and diſowned it; I eſteem him not to deſerve an anſwer. By what I have ſaid it is clear that the ſociety hath no particular Doctrine concerning the Popes authority over Princes, but that they particularly are forbid the teaching of that opinion, which none elſe are known to be. And this I conceive anſwer enough for all that Authours falſe and malioious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſions, of a party of temporal ends, &amp; the reſt of his uncharitable cenſures, for which I pray God to forgive him.</p>
                     <p>The other thing that I would adme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh particularly the Proteſtant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in all love and charity is, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he condemne the Catholicks for the Doctrine which they have taught, he would turn his eyes a little towards
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97877:67"/>his Own Church, where he ſhall find as dangerous Doctrine, not ſo ſay more dangerous. <hi>Luther, Zuinglius, Galvin, Beza, Knox, Goodman,</hi> and divers others have vented ſtrange do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine concerning Soveraignty. <hi>I</hi> will not cite their ſentences, leſt I may ſeem to exprobate: But this I ſay, as <hi>I</hi> do not cenſure any Proteſtant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome have taught dangerous Doctrine, ſo I deſire the Proteſtant will be as favourable to me, and not lay the blame of other mens actions or words on me. As for my part, I do ſincerely make this Proteſtation as in the ſight of God; I do acknowledg his Majeſty CHARLES the II. to be my lawful Soveraign, and leige Lord, <hi>I</hi> believe that I am bound to reſpect, honour and obey him, and that not only for fear but alſo for conſcience ſake, as the Scriptures teach me. <hi>I</hi> do believe that whoſoever reſiſteth him, reſiſteth God; and whoſoever rebelleth againſt him, rebelleth againſt God, and procureth to himſelf damnation. And accordingly I do promiſe to be a true and faithful ſubject to his Majeſty, and not only never to Act againſt him,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97877:67"/>or abett any that ſhall act againſt him, but alſo to defend and maintain, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the beſt of my skill, his life, crown, dignities and prerogatives. If <hi>I</hi> refuſe the oath of Allegiance, as now it is couched, it is not becauſe I refuſe Allegiance, but becauſe I muſt not renounce my faith to God. That to take the oath, as now it lies, is to renounce the Catholick faith, <hi>I</hi> am taught by the example of all former Catholicks in <hi>England,</hi> who though faithful to his Majeſty, yet choſe to loſe their fortunes, liberty and life, rather then to take that Oath, for fear of violating their faith; I am taught ſo by the publick voice of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks and Prieſts now living, who all generally eſteem, it cannot ſafely be taken; I am taught ſo by the general opinion of Proteſtants, who judge thoſe that take that oath to be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, and no more Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks; Finally, <hi>I</hi> am taught ſo by the very title of the Act wherein this Oath was inſerted when it was firſt made. Which is, <hi>an act for the diſcovering and repreſſing Popiſh. Recuſants.</hi> All this maketh me judge it not ſafe in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97877:68"/>to take the Oath as it lyes, for fear of being perjured in that Oath wherein I deſire to be moſt ſtrictly bound to my Soveraign: But if it may ſo pleaſe his ſacred Majeſty, and the honourable houſes of Parliament to make ſuch an oath of Allegiance as may without trenching on conſcience, contain all imaginable civil duty in the ſtrongeſt expreſſions that can be conceived; <hi>I</hi> ſhall be exceeding glad, and moſt ready to take it my ſelf, and invite all others to take it: Nor will I be my own Judge of the legality of any Oath; whatſoever all other prieſts and religious ſhall agree to, that <hi>I</hi> ſhall moſt willingly accept. This is my Proteſtation, to which <hi>I</hi> know all Jſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites in <hi>England</hi> will moſt willingly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, for though they be ſlandered as making a party, and maintaining dangerous doctrine, yet they have no ſuch doctrine, nor party, nor intereſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> but do willingly profeſſe to joyne in whatſoever others ſhall agree.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:97877:68"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CAP. VII.</hi> The last Objection made againſt the Jeſuites, from the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>France.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe laſt Objection neither impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Jeſuites Doctrine, nor their lives, but argueth from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> that ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Jeſuites. Truly if the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of example may here take place, as <hi>I</hi> deſire it ſhould, the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites will be in a very good condition; for the verdict of the greateſt part of Chriſtendom ſtandeth for them. They can fetch examples from all quarters of the world; the Sun never ſets nor riſes, but upon ſome nation where Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites are highly made of. So that their adverſaries urging this argument is but to give them the Que to dilate themſelves in reciting the publick te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies which Religious Orders, Univerſities, Cities, States, Kingdoms, Popes, Emperours, Princes, Nobles,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97877:69"/>and Commons have every where given them. But I will decline this, as having not undertaken to praiſe the Society, but to give a true notion of their lives and Doctrine. True it is, their adverſaries are many, which gives them great occaſion of practiſing vertue, according as it did to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, who ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.9. <hi>Ostium mihi apertum eſt magnum &amp; adverſarii mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, a great door is opened to me and many adverſaries.</hi> But there is main difference betwixt their Friends and their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. Their adverſaries excel in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but their Friends in quality. Their adverſaries are for the moſt part ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of either vertue or learning, or both, their friends perſons of the beſt repute. Their adverſaries act in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate by Libels, in publick by clamours and tumults. Their friends give them juridical teſtimonies, in the face of the world and publick courts. Their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries are carried on by paſſion; their friends by reaſon. Their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries are moved by private diſguſts and ſelf ends; their friends act for the general good and common intereſt. All this I could prove by inſtancing in
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97877:69"/>every particular ſeveral praeſidents in all the Nations of <hi>Europe, Africa, Aſia,</hi> and both <hi>Indies,</hi> as far as the name of Chriſt is known. But I will not commend the ſociety as not having undertaken that task: Only I ſay that there is no Nation under the cope of Heaven, where Catholick religion is tolerated, but that the Jeſuites are alſo allowed, as well as other Prieſts.</p>
                     <p>I come therefore to the Objection, and ſay that the examples of <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> are no motives to make <hi>England</hi> baniſh the Jeſuites, but rather arguments of the contrary. It is good to be wiſe at other mens coſt. <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>France</hi> have repented their acts; and ſurely he cannot be a good friend, and good counſellour, that adviſes <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to do what other nations repent they have done, that is, exhorteth us to imitate other mens faults. The matter is plain; yet becauſe nothing is too plain for them that will not ſee, and do beſides indeavour to caſt a miſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore other mens eyes; Lets look at both the paſſages. And firſt for <hi>Venice.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Spondanus</hi> then in the ſecond <hi>Tome</hi>
                        <pb n="124" facs="tcp:97877:70"/>of his continuation of <hi>Annalls, an.</hi> 1606 relateth how pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, was offended with the <hi>Venetians.</hi> The cauſe of the diſguſt was, that the Senate had made ſome lawes whereby they took to themſelves power over the Clergy in puniſhing their crimes: as alſo they forbid the giving of any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable goods to pious uſes, as to build any Churches or Hoſpitals in their State, without having firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein'd leave of the Senate. Pope <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſhed the Senate of this; they ſleighted his admonitions, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained that they did nothing but what they had juſt authority for. After ſeveral replyes to and fro, the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> perſiſting in their opinion, the Pope proceeded to cenſures. He ſends a <hi>Breve</hi> with the ſentence of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication and Inderdict to all the Biſhops and Prelates of the ſtate of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> with command that if the Senate did not ſatisfy within 24 dayes, then they ſhould publiſh the <hi>Breve,</hi> whereby the Senatours were to be Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and the State interdicted. The Senate on the contrary ſends to all the ſame Biſhops and Prelates a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:97877:70"/>not to publiſh the ſaid Brief. Yet ſome Prelates obeying the Popes authority, the brief waspubliſhed when the time elapſed. And ſo the Duke and Senatours were Excommunicate, and an interdict laid on the whole State. Many contemning the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict celebrated divine offices; ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed it. Among theſe were the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites and the Capuchins, and ſome others, for which they were at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of one Friar <hi>Paul</hi> baniſhed the ſtate. The next year matters were compounded, the Senate took off their lawes, and the pope his cenſures. All others were reſtored, but only the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites whom Friar <hi>Paul</hi> particularly maliced. So the Jeſuites remained out of that State (pope <hi>Paul</hi> and his ſucceſſours for the publick good, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their cauſe fall) till pope <hi>Alexander</hi> that now ſitteth. For this pope toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Embaſſadour of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, <hi>Spain, France,</hi> and other princes, dealt with the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians</hi> to readmit the Jeſuites. The Senate then looking back on what they had done, cancelled their own Act, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it null, and invited the Society
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97877:71"/>their republique, reſtoring them all their houſes and colledges with much honour.</p>
                     <p>This is the ſtory, which I think no man will take for an argument that the Jeſuits are to be baniſhed <hi>England.</hi> The occaſion of their baniſhment was, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the <hi>Popes</hi> cenſure of Interdict and Excommunication, which King <hi>James</hi> doth not deny but that the <hi>Pope</hi> may inflict, as Patriarche of the Weſt. The event was, that the <hi>Venetian</hi> Senate retracted their ſentence, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Jeſuits innocence.</p>
                     <p>Now for the ſtory of <hi>France;</hi> it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened thus. In the year 1594 on the 27 of <hi>December,</hi> one <hi>John Catel,</hi> a perſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us miſcreant attempted on the life of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ry</hi> the Fourth, preſently after his reception at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the cloſing of the long Civil warrs of <hi>France.</hi> But by the bleſſing of God the Felon miſſed of his wicked deſign. For whereas the King was ſtooping to ſalute ſome of his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the wound light on his upper lip, and only ſtruck out one of his teeth with much effuſion of bloud. <hi>Catell</hi> being preſently taken was racked, to confeſs his complices, and who had
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97877:71"/>ſet him on. He never confeſſed any thing that might concern any Jeſuit, neither in nor out of the torture. Yet the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts</hi> and other enemies of the ſociety would needes have it, that the miſcheif was of the Jeſuites plotting, grounded on this only argument, that <hi>Catell,</hi> though then a Student at law, had formerly ſtudied his philoſophy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Jeſuites. Preſently therefore they runtimed to the Colledge, ſeize on all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Jeſuites, ſearch their houſe, and ranſack their papers. Father <hi>Gueret</hi> was the Maſter under whom <hi>Catell</hi> had heard his philoſophy, him therefore they tortured, but finding nothing by his Confeſſion on the rack, or by any witneſſe, they baniſhed him for ever out of <hi>France.</hi> And whereas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the papers belonging to one Father <hi>Guignard,</hi> they found ſomething which had been writ during the time of the Ligue, and it ſeems might be interpreted treaſon, they preſently took him, condemned him, and hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. Then they made an act, ſaith <hi>Monſieur de Thou, Hiſt. lib.</hi> 132. <hi>without order of Judgement, without hearing the partyes, as in a publick ſedition. Non
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:97877:72"/>ſervato juris ordine, neque partibus audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ut in ſeditione &amp; publica graſſatione.</hi> They are the words of <hi>Harley</hi> the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident. In this Act <hi>Catel</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death, and all the Jeſuites of <hi>France</hi> (as far as it then obeyed <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the fourth) ſentenced to perpetual baniſhment, and their goods confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to pious uſes; and further in the ſame ſentence, it was made high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for any to ſend their children out of <hi>France</hi> to ſtudy in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Jeſuites ſchools. And that they might not ſeem to be ſevere only againſt the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, they baniſht for nine years the father of <hi>Catel</hi> a Merchant of cloth: his fault was, that whereas his ſon had acquainted him with his deſign of killing the King, he had not revealed it in time, nor uſed means to prevent it, though he did diſſwade it. Finally the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> to make the Jeſuits eternally ignominious, erected a pillar in the place where <hi>Catels</hi> houſe had ſtood, with an inſcription that might carry to future ages the infamy of <hi>Catels</hi> fact, attributed to the Jeſuits. The pillar was erected, and the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence executed in all the Kings domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:97877:72"/>except only the Parliament of <hi>Tolouſe</hi> and <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> and the places depending on that Parliament. For the Parliament of <hi>Tolouſe</hi> ſeeing the injuſtice of the proceeding commanded that no town or place belonging to their judicature ſhould obey the Act made at <hi>Paris.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All this is related by <hi>de Thou, Peter Mathien, Scipion Duepleix, Spondanus,</hi> and others. King <hi>Henry</hi> ſat not yet faſt enough in the ſaddle to conteſt with the Parliament of <hi>Paris.</hi> For though the Parliaments of <hi>France,</hi> be nothing like our Parliaments of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (ours being a repreſentative of the Nation, with whom the King can make and unmake lawes; theirs only a number of Lawyers in ſeveral courts of Judicature to take cognizance of particular caſes and crimes) yet King <hi>Henry,</hi> thought not fit to ſcratch the wounds of <hi>France,</hi> not yet well healed, by offending them who had ſo lately been reconciled, and had during the Ligue droven a ſtrong intereſt for the ſide they took. But as ſoon as the firſt ſtorme was over he began by little and little to ſhew his inclinations to the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:97877:73"/>Society, hearing willingly thoſe that ſpoke for them, and himſelf ſpeaking favourably of them; till at length when things were ripe for a good iſſue he reſolved to recall them. The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris,</hi> on the contrary, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured might &amp; main to oppoſe them, and to that end after many other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, one of the Preſidents, by name <hi>Harley,</hi> towards the end of the year 1603. made in a full aſſembly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King a long and ſharp inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive againſt the Jeſuites, all tending to this, that for the good of the King and Kingdom the Jeſuits ought not to be recalled, but continue baniſhed.</p>
                     <p>When K. <hi>Henry</hi> had patiently heard him out, he was pleaſed to ſpeak him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and plead for the Society, retort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and anſwering all that <hi>Harley</hi> had ſaid, ſo dextrouſly that all admired his vivacity of memory and judgment, and his ſtrong nervous eloquence, which made him King not only of men, but of Eloquence alſo. I mean to ſet down his ſpeech as it was printed in Latine firſt, then in Engliſh in the year 1611. I taking that to be an authentical copy. For whereas in the year 1610. the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:97877:73"/>againſt the ſociety grew very rife, by occaſion of the untimely death of <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. the friends of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety thought it neceſſary to reprint the ſpeech, (then freſh in the memory of many) and to joyne it with a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration wherein the Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the Society's innocency and merits, and a Conſtitution of <hi>Lewis the XIII.</hi> by which the Society was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in all the priviledges granted by his father <hi>Henry IV.</hi> All theſe were put out together and tranſlated into many languages to confute (as in effect they did) and ſilence the calumny of <hi>Henry IV.</hi> death, of which the adverſaries of the ſociety had made many ſtories run in moſt of the languages of <hi>Europe.</hi> Out of this copy therefore I intend to take the ſpeech. But becauſe I have mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the death of <hi>Henry IV.</hi> I will ſay ſomething of that ſtory before I ſet down the ſpeech.</p>
                     <p>On the 14. day of <hi>May</hi> 1610 this great King was murdered in his coach by a perfidious villan named <hi>Francis Ravaillac,</hi> who being often examined and tortured, alwaies proteſted that he was never induced by any man living
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:97877:74"/>to this fact; and further, that he had not communicated his deſign to any. Yet they who by <hi>Catels</hi> fact had trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed over the ſociety, and procured their baniſhment, (thinking now they had a good occaſion to wreck their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt the Jeſuits in the nonage of their new King whom they could not hurt whilſt the father lived) ſpreadma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny libels againſt the Jeſuits to make them ſeem guilty of that horrid Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide.</p>
                     <p>For this purpoſe they voiced that <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaillac</hi> had learnt his miſchief out of <hi>Mariana,</hi> and ſome did not ſtick to ſay, that he had all <hi>Mariana</hi> without book: But he being examined was found not to know ſo much as <hi>Mariana's</hi> name, and beſides he never underſtood latine. Howſoever that which might give ſome colour to the noiſe was, that the ſchool of <hi>Sorbon</hi> renewed a decree which had been made in the yean 1413. wherein the doctrine of Killing Kings was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned according to the Council of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> This decree was made the 4. of <hi>July</hi> 1610. And the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> ſoon after cauſed <hi>Mariana's</hi> book <hi>de Rege et institutione Regis,</hi> to be burnt,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:97877:74"/>which all reflected on the Jeſuits. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Parliament on the 26 of <hi>Novem.</hi> then following condemued the treatiſe of Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> againſt <hi>Barklay, de poteſtate ſummi pontificis in tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus,</hi> but the K. of <hi>France</hi> 4 daies after iſſued a contrary decree, to caſhiere that Act of the Parliament, and publickly cleered the Jeſuites of all ſuſpition of his fathers death. The King being then in his minority was aſſiſted by the Qu. Regent his Mother, the P. of <hi>Conde,</hi> the Count of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> Princes of the blood, the D. of <hi>Mayenne,</hi> the L. Chancellour, the D. of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> of <hi>Lacerdeene,</hi> of <hi>Bois, Daulphin,</hi> Marſhal of <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. this made the fathers innocency ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that none durſt any further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them.</p>
                     <p>All this I have mentioned for two reaſons, the firſt is becauſe <hi>I</hi> find that ſome Engliſh books take up the French ſlanders, and make much of the decree for condemning <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> whereas notwithſtanding they might have taken notice that that decree was recalled and annulled by the King, Princes, and Councel, and the Jeſuits freed from the aſperſion of the Kings death, which
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:97877:75"/>without any the leaſt appearance of probability was by meer calumny ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to them.</p>
                     <p n="2">2ly. <hi>I</hi> take notice of this decree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will ſhew what Judgment the reader make of ſome other decrees: he may gueſſe by this whether that be not true which <hi>Spondanus</hi> ſaith <hi>ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> 1626. <hi>numero ſecundo;</hi> where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken notice of the ſtrife of <hi>Sorbon</hi> concerning <hi>Santareles</hi> book, and the cenſures of it, he hath theſe words. <hi>Haec doctorum Sorbonicorum diſſidia non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde procedebant, quam ex occultis ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis ſeminibus, quae a multis fovebantur. Theſe diſſentions of the</hi> Sorbon <hi>Doctours did not proceed from any thing elſe, but from hidden ſeeds of Schiſme, which many did nouriſh.</hi> This he doth not ſay (nor do <hi>I</hi>) as though the book of <hi>Santarel</hi> were not juſtly condemned, ſince the King, as <hi>Spondamus</hi> there ſaith, ſignified to <hi>Sorbon</hi> that that book was already ſuppreſſed at <hi>Rome</hi> by the Pope, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned by all learned men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they needed not trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with giving their cenſures. But the violence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heſe Doctours proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> to inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:97877:75"/>bent to Schiſme. And he addeth how the Cardinal <hi>Rochefcault</hi> took oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion from theſe ſtirs of <hi>Sorbon</hi> (which was for a good part of that year 26 bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in Centures) to write a book which he dedicated to the King with this title <hi>Of conſerving the unity of the Church.</hi> This unity, ſaith <hi>Spondanus,</hi> the <hi>Sorbons</hi> went about to tear in pieces, <hi>quam isti diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere ſtudebant,</hi> all which well weighed ſhewes that the authorities which <hi>A. G.</hi> layeth as a foundation in his <hi>questions concerning the oath of Allegiance</hi> cannot be a guid for us. It is not ſafe to be lead by them who endeavour to tear in pieces the unity of the church, <hi>qui u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem Eccleſiae diſcerpere student.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But I have made a long direſſion, Now then I will give you the ſpeech of that great King, and great Protector and Patron of the ſociety. And with it I will end, for I know not where I can end better, then with the Oracle of that wiſe Monarchs judgment, which <hi>I</hi> hope for our dread Soveraigns ſake, who is his Grandchild, and heir of his eminent perfections, will be welcome to all, and <hi>I</hi> am ſure containeth a ſumme of all that needs be ſaid in defence of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:97877:76"/>eſpecially if we conſider that his words were followed with ſuch effects as the cancelling the act, the recalling the Jeſuits into <hi>France,</hi> the founding many colledges (particularly that roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al one of <hi>La Fleche</hi>) the giving his ſon to be educated by the ſociety, and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the bequeathing his heart to them.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:97877:76"/>
                  <head>The Speech of <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. King of <hi>France</hi> in behalf of the Jeſuits.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Nobility of the Court of</hi> Paris, <hi>and a great part of the Parliament being come to the Kings palace,</hi> Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley <hi>one of the Preſidents of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</hi> Paris <hi>addreſſing himſelf to his Majeſty, pronounced a ſtudied invective againſt the Jeſuits wherein he urged all that which the enemies of the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had premeditated. All his ſpeech cloſed in this, that the ſociety of Jeſus ought not to be recalled into</hi> France, <hi>but continue baniſht. The King reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this manner,</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1.</hi> THeicare you ſhew of me and my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is grateful to me; albeit you ſeem not to have throughly weighed the things you demand, nor are you, as yet, ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with my thoughts, as I am with yours.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="138" facs="tcp:97877:77"/>
                           <hi>2.</hi> You deem the weal of my Kingdom to conſiſt in the propoſition you have made; you tell me it is a matter that deſerves to be moſt carefully deliberated. And I tell you, you have ſaid nothing which I have not most carefully weighed, and moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently examined by my ſelf theſe eight or nine years.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3.</hi> You take your ſelves for men of great understandiag and experience in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. Bat believe me I know as well as You all that hath been in controverſie in this matter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4.</hi> Firſt of all you object to the Fathers of the Society, the Aſſembly of Poiſſy;<note n="*">The Clergy held an Aſſembly at <hi>Poiſſy</hi> an. <hi>1561.</hi> in which the ſociety was allowed of, and admitted though not fully.</note> but without cauſe. For if there had been at that place others like many of them, the Catholick cauſe would have had a more happy ſucceſſe. therefore that which you turne to their diſpraiſe, any just <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpire will attribute to their vertue. But that which I moſt wonder at your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for is, that ſo prepoſterouſly you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the ſociety of ambition, whereas the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:97877:77"/>fathers of the ſociety with a conſtant ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, have ever refuſed all honour &amp; prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Political: and which is more, they bind themſelves by vow not only not to aſpire to honours, but even to refuſe the ſame when they are freely offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto them. Conſider their whole courſe of life, and you ſhall find that all their ambition is to labour for to help all, and that without any pretence of interest or gain. They value not the expences of their own pains, ſo they may profit many.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5.</hi> But you call into queſtion the very name of the ſociety of Jeſus, and for that you tax them. But ſee with what reaſon. For if they muſt be blamed for that holy name, what ſhall we ſay for thoſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons who take their name from the most bleſſed Trinity? And your daughters here at <hi>Paris;</hi> what will you think of them that call themſelves <hi>Daughters of God?</hi> Finally how will you cenſure my Knights, who are called of the Holy Ghost? Truly I do not more diſlike them that take their name from Chriſt, then any other.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6.</hi> You object that the Divines of <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> condemned the Jeſuites. I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:97877:78"/>it. But they condemned them being innocent, unknown, and unheard. For this I call to witneſſe, thoſe very Divines themſelves, who now admit them, whom their predeceſſours baniſhed, and honour them whom they contemned; nay they praiſe now and extoll thoſe that were condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſtick not to take them for their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors, &amp; Maſters, in all kind of learning.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7.</hi> You tell me the Jeſuits have hitherto remained in <hi>France</hi> only by connivance. Here I acknowledg, and reverence the divine providence, that hath reſerved this honour for me, not yet atchived by others, that I ſhould establiſh in this Realme the ſociety of Jeſus, which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath had no ſetled abode in <hi>France.</hi> My Predeceſſours have received the ſociety, I will Patronize and preſerve them.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8.</hi> Peradventure you will turne to the Jeſuites diſcredit, that for which you ought to praiſe and honour them: The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Paris</hi> earnestly and openly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them. And what, I pray, was the cauſe of this oppoſition? All was, that the Fathers did not only equal others in
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:97877:78"/>learning and induſtry, but alſo went far beyond them. A clear testimony of this is the great number of youth that frequented the fathers ſchools, where to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with learning they learnt vertue. But to ſtop this oppoſition, I will make a Decree that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> ſhall no more oppoſe them. And this you will be glad of.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9.</hi> But you will tell me, that the ableſt of your Parliament got not their learning of the Jeſuits. This I will not much gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay. For the ablest of you, as they excell in learning ſo they exceed in years. Theſe got their learning in forreign nations, before the ſociety ſet foot in <hi>France.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did not ſo, and ſo I am certain they think and ſpeak otherwiſe. And what need they ſpeak? the matter it ſelf ſpeaks. We our ſelves ſaw how at the departure of the ſociety out of <hi>France,</hi> all the muſes ſeemed to depart. Our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity was deſert and mourned: thoſe came ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom at it, who before dayly in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers frequented the Fathers. Yea many departed the Realme, and forſook their country to study in the ſocieties ſchools; nor could your Decrees or Threats ſtop them.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="142" facs="tcp:97877:79"/>
                           <hi>10.</hi> You ſay the Fathers joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Ligue, that is not to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to their fault, but to the iniquity of the times. But this I perſwade my ſelf, upon the aſſurance I have of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of their Conſciences, that they will become ſuch towards me, as it behoveth them, who mindful of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, deſire to ſhew themſelves most grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>11.</hi> Now ſome of you impoſe on the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers a new crime, and peradventure as yet unheard of, ſaying, that they draw to their order young men of the moſt forwardneſs and beſt diſpoſitions. An unpardonable crime: yet I praiſe them and eſteem them particularly for this that you condemne. Do not we, though in a different matter, do the ſelf ſame? A Captain that is to raiſe Souldiers, does he not cull out the choiceſt, and leave the meaneſt and lest hopeful? In your Parliament, when you chooſe a new Court, or fill up an old, do you preferr the unlearnedst, and leaſt apt for buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? If the Jeſuites ſhould put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Masters in their ſchools, or in
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:97877:79"/>their Churches ignorant Preachers, would you not with reaſon blame them? What of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is it that the Jeſuits ſhould provide the fitteſt they can, both for Church and Schools.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>12.</hi> That ſlander which concerns the Jeſuits treaſure, is as falſe as common. Go viſit all the Colledges in <hi>France,</hi> ſearch all their treaſures, ſum all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and you will ſcarce find twelve, or at moſt fifteen thouſand crowns. I know well how poor and ſlender furniture and proviſion was both at <hi>Lyons</hi> and <hi>Bourge.</hi> Nevertheleſſe <hi>30</hi> or <hi>40</hi> perſons were to be fed in each of thoſe colledges; whereas their yearly revenues was ſcarcely ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for eight Maſters.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>13.</hi> The vow of obedience with which they tye themſelves to the Pope doth not oblige them to be more faithfull to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes, then to us. Neither is there in that Vow any thing contrary to the oath which they will ſwear unto me. They will attempt nothing (I am ſure) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Prince. That Vow to the Pope, bindeth them to go to barbarous and ſavage Nations that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:97877:80"/>them to the Catholick church. The whole world teſtifyeth that the remoteſt regions of the <hi>Indies,</hi> together with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Hereticks, have been by their pains and learned endeavours, brought to Chriſts fold. I remember I have often ſaid, that if the labour of Spaniſh Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be ſo profitable for <hi>Spain,</hi> why ſhould not <hi>France</hi> with reaſon expect the ſame? Is that Kingdom more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate and flouriſhing then this? <hi>Spain</hi> is loved by the Spaniards, and why ſhould the <hi>French</hi> hate their Native ſoil?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>14.</hi> But as you are wont to ſay, theſe men ſeek to be admitted into Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and Kingdomes what way ſoever they can. Pray you is this an offence? 'Tis the cuſtome of all that follow the inſtinct of nature. I my ſelf, by what means I could, ſought to get my Crown. Howſoever we cannot but admire the Fathers conſtant patience whereby they go through ſo great and hard matters, and bear ſo many and ſo heavy croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="145" facs="tcp:97877:80"/>
                           <hi>15.</hi> Neither do I Eſteem them the worſe, for that they be ſo obſervant of their Rules and Constitutions. This is that whereby the ſociety doth increaſe, flouriſh and better it ſelf every day more and more. For this reaſon I thought not good to change any of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions or Rules, though I have made ſome change in others, which was not approved of all. But that's no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>16.</hi> The Fathers of the ſociety have many back friends, among ſome that ſeem Holy and Religious perſons, who ſpeak ill of them. This no wiſe man will wonder at. Our age is not come to that ſanctity, that ignorance ſhould ceaſe to hate learning, or corruption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners leave to envy integrity of life. It was ſo in times past, and ſo 'tis ſtill. Theſe moathes are alwayes gnawing on learned works. No proſperity ſo cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, that can ſcape the tooth of malice, hatred and envy, alwaies attend the higheſt things. I obſerved: when it was conſulted about the recalling of the Jeſuits into <hi>France,</hi> that two
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:97877:81"/>ſorts of men did ſpecially oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Hereticks, and looſe living Churchmen: the one was moved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by their bad faith, the other by their bad life. But I am ſo far from being hereby moved to alter my intended pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that I am more confirmed in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>17.</hi> The Fathers of the ſociety, ſpeak and think honourably of the Pope, ſo they ſhould, and ſo do I; I joyn with them, ſince I am certain that in aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and defending the Popes authority, they differ not from other Catholick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>18.</hi> Neither did their Doctrine ever give occaſion to Clergie-men to deny me tribute. Nor is there any to be found whom theſe Fathers words or books animated to killing of Kings. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſome have patcht together to bring them to Diſcredit, is all a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and meer Fable. Thirty Years and more are paſſed ſince the Fathers began to inſtruct the Youth of <hi>France</hi> both in Vertue and Learning. Of theſe ſome
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:97877:81"/>have gone through with all their ſtudies in their Schools. Others have broke off, and applyed themſelves to Phiſick or Law. Tell me whether any of theſe ever learnt of their Masters to lay hands upon Kings, and to kill them? I tell You the Fathers are ſo clear, that they are content to appeal even to their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies judgement. There are ſome Pulpit-Men among the Hereticks, who were trained up in Fathers Schools: ask theſe Men their judgment concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Jeſuits lives and Doctrine: But whoſe cauſe is ſo good as to deſire to be tryed by Enemies? Yet I am ſure in their caſe this has been done, The Miniſters have been asked their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Jeſuits: and they have given no other anſwer, but, That the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its Lives cannot be Reprehended, and for their Doctrine, that it is in too clear a Sunne for to be be questioned. Certes few can be found that will dare to ſtand to their Enemies judgment, their ſecurity of conſcience muſt needs be great, that fears not any Adverſaries Verdict</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>19.</hi> The Confeſſion of <hi>Barriere,</hi> who attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:97877:82"/>ſomething againſt my perſon, doth not infringe that which I have ſaid. For ſo far was any Jeſuit from that fact (which you nevertheleſs affirm) that one of theſe Fathers of good credit adviſed me of it in time, and another of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted and deterred <hi>Barriere</hi> from his attempt, propoſing to him Gods heavy Judgements due to ſuch Malefactors.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>20.</hi> As for <hi>Catel,</hi> all imaginable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, were not able to wreſt the least word againſt, <hi>Varadius</hi> or any one Father of the Society. If this be not ſo why ſpared you the guilty? Why let you them go when you had them faſt? why puniſhed you them not according to your Law and Court?</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>21.</hi> But to grant you that that never was; ſuppoſe ſome one of the ſociety had attempted againſt my perſon. Will you condemn all the Apoſtles for one <hi>Judas?</hi> ſhall the puniſhment light on my head, for whatſoever any of my Souldiers ſhall treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe in military licenſe? I acknowledge the hand of God, whoſe will it was to have me preſſed and humbled at that time; the ſame hand raiſed me and ſet me ſafe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Gods goodneſſe and providence be
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:97877:82"/>thanked. I have learnt to forget and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give injuries for Gods ſake, as I willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do for that King who is greater then my ſelf. And now I will be ſo far from remembring injuries done unto me, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging the ſame, that I will dayly offer up praiers to God for my enemies. All of us have need of Gods mercy, which is no waies better to be obtained, then by promptly and readily pardoning thoſe who have offended <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:83"/>
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>Page 13 <hi>Dominus</hi> read <hi>Divinius,</hi> p. 19 miſtery r. maſtery, p. 22. World, revealed r. World and revealed, <hi>ibidem</hi> ſwarm, r. ſwarve, p. 24 yea, r. yet, p. 55 to the known, r. to all the known p. 72 to relent r. reſent, p. 76 and carry away the ball; r. and ſeem to them to carry away the bell; p. 78 publiſhing, r. palliating; p. 134. the reader make, the reader may make.</p>
                  <p>Some other faults there are of leſſer note, and errours in the interpunctions which the Juditious Reader will eaſily correct.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:83"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:85"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:85"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:86"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:86"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:87"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:87"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:88"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:88"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:89"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:89"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:91"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97877:91"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97877:92"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97877:92"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97877:93"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97877:93"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97877:94"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97877:94"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97877:95"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97877:95"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97877:96"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97877:96"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97877:97"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97877:97"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97877:98"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97877:98"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97877:99"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97877:99"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:97877:100"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:97877:100"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:97877:101"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97877:101"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:97877:102"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:97877:102"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97877:103"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:97877:103"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:97877:104"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97877:104"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:97877:105"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:97877:105"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97877:106"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97877:106"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97877:107"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:97877:107"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:97877:108"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:97877:108"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
